[

{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Which stone is used for buildings located in industrial cities?",
    "options": [
        "Marble slab",
        "Compact sandstone",
        "Gneiss",
        "Slate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compact sandstone"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Rubble masonry is divided into:",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "6",
        "10"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "6"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Random rubble masonry stones are:",
    "options": [
        "Dressed with chisel",
        "Dressed with hammer",
        "Dressed with axe",
        "Plain dressed"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dressed with chisel"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The nodules found in flint rubble are:",
    "options": [
        "Fly ash nodules",
        "Feldspar nodules",
        "Mica nodules",
        "Silica nodules"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Silica nodules"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "For masonry in arches, which type of joint is used?",
    "options": [
        "Butt",
        "Table",
        "Rebated",
        "Dowel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rebated"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "What proportion of cement mortar is used for stone masonry?",
    "options": [
        "1:6",
        "1:3",
        "1:8",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:3"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Ashlar masonry uses:",
    "options": [
        "Dimension stones",
        "Polygonal stones",
        "Quarry dressed stones",
        "Square stones"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dimension stones"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Which is intermediate between rubble masonry and ashlar masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Rubble blocks in one course",
        "Ashlar rubble coursed",
        "Ashlar blocks in one course",
        "Rubble ashlar"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ashlar blocks in one course"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Great labor skill is required for laying:",
    "options": [
        "Cut rubble",
        "Ashlar fine masonry",
        "Ashlar rough masonry",
        "Dry rubble masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dry rubble masonry"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "For stone masonry, which of the following should not be followed?",
    "options": [
        "Header stones should be dumb-bell shaped",
        "Cure for 2–3 weeks",
        "Construction should be raised uniformly",
        "Stones used should be wet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header stones should be dumb-bell shaped"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "How many types of brick masonry are possible?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "5",
        "6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Which brick is laid with its length in the direction of the wall?",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Flemish",
        "Stretcher",
        "English"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "In brick masonry, which of the following should be avoided?",
    "options": [
        "Horizontal joints",
        "Queen closer",
        "Brick bat",
        "Vertical joints"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vertical joints"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Compared to English bond, which bond looks better in appearance?",
    "options": [
        "Flemish",
        "Double Flemish",
        "Single Flemish",
        "Poly Flemish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Double Flemish"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Flemish bond is more expensive than English bond.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "In herringbone bond, bricks are laid in lines inclined at:",
    "options": [
        "60°, central",
        "60°, vertical",
        "45°, central",
        "45°, vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "45°, central"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Portions of bricks cut into half their width are called:",
    "options": [
        "Half division",
        "Half closer",
        "Half bed",
        "Half bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Half bat"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "In English bond, what is placed at the beginning of every header course to avoid vertical joints?",
    "options": [
        "Queen closer",
        "Half bat",
        "Three-fourth bat",
        "King closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Bricks used at the corners of walls in a structure are called:",
    "options": [
        "Spalls",
        "Quoins",
        "Hearing",
        "Side"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quoins"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Which bond consists of one course of headers to three or five courses of stretchers?",
    "options": [
        "Dutch bond",
        "Zig-zag bond",
        "English garden-wall bond",
        "Facing bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "English garden-wall bond"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Which IS code gives practice for brickwork?",
    "options": [
        "IS 2212",
        "IS 3102",
        "IS 3466",
        "IS 1077"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 2212"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "How many main components are used for preparing concrete?",
    "options": [
        "5",
        "3",
        "2",
        "4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Which is the most common alternative to cement in concrete?",
    "options": [
        "Slag",
        "Fly ash",
        "Asphalt",
        "Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Asphalt"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "What is the ideal water-cement ratio used for hand mixing?",
    "options": [
        "0.4–0.5",
        "0.5–0.6",
        "0.6–1",
        "1.6–2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.5–0.6"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Which IS code gives specifications about water used in concrete?",
    "options": [
        "IS 456",
        "IS 383",
        "IS 565",
        "IS 3012"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 456"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "How many types of chemical admixtures are there?",
    "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "4",
        "5"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Retarders are used for:",
    "options": [
        "High-rise building construction",
        "Repair work",
        "Cold weather condition",
        "Grinding large quantities of cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Grinding large quantities of cement"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "For making white concrete, what is added?",
    "options": [
        "Fly ash",
        "Metakaolin",
        "Rice husk",
        "Pigment"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metakaolin"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "As the water-cement ratio increases, what also increases?",
    "options": [
        "Compressive strength",
        "Tensile strength",
        "Bleeding",
        "Workability"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Workability"
},
{
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Which of the following is an example of a plasticizer?",
    "options": [
        "Hydroxylated carboxylic acid",
        "Fluorosilicate",
        "Gypsum",
        "Surkhi"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydroxylated carboxylic acid"
},
{
    "number": 33,
    "question": "Which component of concrete provides the desired compressive strength?",
    "options": [
        "Water",
        "Cement",
        "Aggregates",
        "Admixture"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aggregates"
},
{
    "number": 34,
    "question": "The mix proportion of M20 grade concrete is:",
    "options": [
        "1:3:6",
        "1:1.5:3",
        "1:1:2",
        "1:2:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:1.5:3"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "When a brick is cut, what is it called in length?",
    "options": [
        "King closer",
        "Queen closer",
        "Half bat",
        "Stretcher"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "What is a pug mill used for?",
    "options": [
        "Preparation of clay",
        "Mixing mortar",
        "Grinding cement",
        "Burning bricks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Preparation of clay"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Max water absorption for 1st class bricks?",
    "options": [
        "10%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15%"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Desired max efflorescence presence?",
    "options": [
        "10%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10%"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Crushing strength of 1st class brick?",
    "options": [
        "7 N/mm2",
        "8.5 N/mm2",
        "10 N/mm2",
        "12 N/mm2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "7 N/mm2"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Max efflorescence for bricks?",
    "options": [
        "12%",
        "15%",
        "18%",
        "20%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "12%"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Firing temp range for bricks?",
    "options": [
        "700–900 C",
        "800–1000 C",
        "900–1200 C",
        "1000–1300 C"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "900–1200 C"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Types of brick bonding?",
    "options": [
        "4 types",
        "5 types",
        "6 types",
        "7 types"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4 types"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Main purpose of frog in bricks?",
    "options": [
        "Reduce weight",
        "Improve shape",
        "Key joint between brick and mortar",
        "Absorb water"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Key joint between brick and mortar"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Cause of brick efflorescence?",
    "options": [
        "Soluble salts in clay",
        "Improper burning",
        "Excess alumina",
        "Over drying"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soluble salts in clay"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "King closer relates to?",
    "options": [
        "Concrete work",
        "Stone masonry",
        "Timber work",
        "Brick masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brick masonry"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Crushing strength of 1st class brick?",
    "options": [
        "8 N/mm2",
        "9 N/mm2",
        "10.5 N/mm2",
        "12 N/mm2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10.5 N/mm2"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Max water absorption after 24hr immersion?",
    "options": [
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%",
        "30%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20%"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "How many types of brick bonds?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "5",
        "6",
        "7"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Brick laid with length along wall?",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Frog",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Size of modular brick?",
    "options": [
        "19cm x 9cm x 9cm",
        "20cm x 10cm x 10cm",
        "21cm x 10cm x 9cm",
        "22cm x 11cm x 7cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "19cm x 9cm x 9cm"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Component giving plasticity to earth?",
    "options": [
        "Silica",
        "Alumina",
        "Lime",
        "Iron oxide"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alumina"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Pug mill use in brick production?",
    "options": [
        "Mixing sand",
        "Grinding lime",
        "Tempering",
        "Firing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tempering"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Excess silica in brick causes?",
    "options": [
        "Brittle on burning",
        "Soft texture",
        "Excess plasticity",
        "Swelling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brittle on burning"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Harmful component in brick clay?",
    "options": [
        "Silica",
        "Iron pyrite",
        "Alumina",
        "Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Iron pyrite"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Rain on hot bricks causes?",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Warping",
        "Scabbing",
        "Spalling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scabbing"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Basic fire brick is made of?",
    "options": [
        "Silica brick",
        "Alumina brick",
        "Magnesia brick",
        "Chrome brick"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Magnesia brick"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Bricks for steel industry furnaces?",
    "options": [
        "Acid refractory",
        "Basic refractory",
        "Neutral refractory",
        "Silica refractory"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Acid refractory"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Terracotta is fired in?",
    "options": [
        "Open sun",
        "Clamp",
        "Kiln",
        "Pit"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Kiln"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Standard brick weight?",
    "options": [
        "2000 grams",
        "2500 grams",
        "2800 grams",
        "3000 grams"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3000 grams"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Max water absorption for 1st class brick?",
    "options": [
        "10%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15%"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Moisture before firing moulded bricks?",
    "options": [
        "3%",
        "5%",
        "7%",
        "10%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3%"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Max water absorption after 24hr immersion?",
    "options": [
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%",
        "30%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20%"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Compressive strength (IS 1077) of burnt clay bricks?",
    "options": [
        "100–150 kg/cm2",
        "200–250 kg/cm2",
        "300–320 kg/cm2",
        "350–350 kg/cm2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "35350 kg/cm2"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "No. of bricks per m3 of masonry?",
    "options": [
        "400",
        "450",
        "500",
        "550"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "500"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "Bricks for hidden masonry?",
    "options": [
        "1st class",
        "2nd class",
        "3rd class",
        "Over burnt"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2nd class"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "When a brick is cut, what is it called in length?",
    "options": [
        "King closer",
        "Queen closer",
        "Corbel",
        "Bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "What is a pug mill used for?",
    "options": [
        "Preparation of clay",
        "Molding clay",
        "Drying bricks",
        "Burning bricks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Preparation of clay"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "What is the maximum water absorption allowed for first-class bricks?",
    "options": [
        "12%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15%"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The desirable maximum efflorescence present should not exceed?",
    "options": [
        "10%",
        "4%",
        "5%",
        "8%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10%"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Crushing strength of first-class brick is:",
    "options": [
        "7 N/mm²",
        "10 N/mm²",
        "8 N/mm²",
        "5 N/mm²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "7 N/mm²"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The efflorescence in bricks should not exceed?",
    "options": [
        "12%",
        "14%",
        "15%",
        "20%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "12%"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Bricks are fired at what temperature range?",
    "options": [
        "500–700°C",
        "700–900°C",
        "900–1200°C",
        "1200–1500°C"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "900–1200°C"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Brick bonding is possible in how many ways?",
    "options": [
        "4 types",
        "2 types",
        "5 types",
        "6 types"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4 types"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "What is the main purpose of a frog in a brick?",
    "options": [
        "To emboss the manufacturer’s name",
        "To reduce weight",
        "To provide key joint between brick and mortar",
        "To improve insulation by making it hollow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "To provide key joint between brick and mortar"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Efflorescence in bricks is caused by:",
    "options": [
        "Soluble salts present in clay used for brick making",
        "High porosity",
        "High silt content in soil",
        "Overburning"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soluble salts present in clay used for brick making"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "King closer is related to:",
    "options": [
        "Doors and windows",
        "King post truss",
        "Queen post truss",
        "Brick masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brick masonry"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Crushing strength of first-class brick:",
    "options": [
        "3 N/mm²",
        "5.5 N/mm²",
        "10.5 N/mm²",
        "7.5 N/mm²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10.5 N/mm²"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Water absorption of first-class brick after 24 hours immersion should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "25%",
        "20%",
        "15%",
        "18%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20%"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Types of brick masonry:",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "5",
        "9"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Which brick is laid with its length along the wall direction?",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Flemish",
        "Stretcher",
        "English"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Size of a modular brick:",
    "options": [
        "19cm × 9cm × 9cm",
        "23cm × 11.4cm × 7.6cm",
        "25cm × 12.5cm × 7.6cm",
        "29cm × 9cm × 9cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "19cm × 9cm × 9cm"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Which component gives plasticity to the earth to mold bricks?",
    "options": [
        "Silica",
        "Alumina",
        "Lime",
        "Magnesia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alumina"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "In brick manufacturing, pug mill is used in which operation?",
    "options": [
        "Weathering",
        "Mixing",
        "Tempering",
        "Burning"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tempering"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Excess silica in bricks makes them:",
    "options": [
        "Brittle when burnt",
        "Melting on burning",
        "Cracking on drying",
        "Warping"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brittle when burnt"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Which of the following is harmful in brick-making soil?",
    "options": [
        "Iron oxide",
        "Iron pyrite",
        "Alkalis",
        "Magnesia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Iron pyrite"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Deformation of brick shape due to rain on hot bricks is called?",
    "options": [
        "Spot",
        "Check",
        "Scab",
        "Blister"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scab"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Basic fire bricks are made of:",
    "options": [
        "Silica bricks",
        "Gannister bricks",
        "Magnesia bricks",
        "Chromite bricks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Magnesia bricks"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Bricks used in steel industry furnaces should be:",
    "options": [
        "Acid refractory",
        "Basic refractory",
        "Neutral refractory",
        "Heavy duty"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Acid refractory"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Terracotta is fired in:",
    "options": [
        "Pug mill",
        "Reverberatory furnace",
        "Kiln",
        "Puddling furnace"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Kiln"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Standard brick weight should be:",
    "options": [
        "1000 g",
        "1500 g",
        "2500 g",
        "3000 g"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3000 g"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Max water absorption for first-class brick:",
    "options": [
        "12%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15%"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Moulded bricks should be dried before firing to approx. what moisture content?",
    "options": [
        "3%",
        "6%",
        "10%",
        "20%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3%"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "A good brick should not absorb more water than?",
    "options": [
        "20%",
        "15%",
        "10%",
        "25% of its dry weight"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20%"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "According to IS 1077, compressive strength of burnt clay brick is:",
    "options": [
        "100 kg/cm²",
        "150 kg/cm²",
        "100–150 kg/cm²",
        "35–350 kg/cm²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "35–350 kg/cm²"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "No. of bricks per cubic meter of brick masonry:",
    "options": [
        "400",
        "450",
        "500",
        "550"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "500"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "For hidden masonry work, bricks used should be:",
    "options": [
        "1st class",
        "2nd class",
        "3rd class",
        "4th class"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2nd class"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "The surface of the abutment on which the arch rests is known as:",
    "options": [
        "Span",
        "Keystone",
        "Skewback",
        "Crown"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Skewback"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "A course of stone provided just below a cornice is called:",
    "options": [
        "Blocking",
        "Coping",
        "Frieze",
        "Parapet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Frieze"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "When used widely on the face work of brick and stone masonry, it refers to:",
    "options": [
        "Flush pointing",
        "Struck pointing",
        "Vee pointing",
        "Tuck pointing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vee pointing"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "A bat is:",
    "options": [
        "The wall between face and backing",
        "Not exposed to weather",
        "A brick cut to width",
        "A brick cut such that one long face remains uncut"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "A brick cut to width"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "The underside of an arch is called:",
    "options": [
        "Extrados",
        "Intrados",
        "Crown",
        "Voussoirs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Intrados"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The commonly adopted slope for concrete in road work is:",
    "options": [
        "12 to 25",
        "20 to 28",
        "25 to 50",
        "50 to 100"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20 to 28"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Carving cannot be done easily on:",
    "options": [
        "Marble",
        "Limestone",
        "Granite",
        "Sandstone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Granite"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Tiles are fixed on wooden floors using:",
    "options": [
        "Emulsified bitumen and cement",
        "Bitumen only",
        "Thermoset plastic",
        "Nitro cellulose"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Emulsified bitumen and cement"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "The vertical face of an opening left in walls for fixing doors and windows is called:",
    "options": [
        "Brick steps",
        "Brick parapet",
        "Brick jamb",
        "Cavity wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brick jamb"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Jambs and mullions are:",
    "options": [
        "Vertical seatings",
        "Inclined ceilings",
        "Horizontal seatings",
        "Zig-zag seatings"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Horizontal seatings"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Stretcher bond is suitable for walls of thickness:",
    "options": [
        "1 brick",
        "1½ bricks",
        "½ brick",
        "2 bricks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "½ brick"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Mixed R.C. beams can be preferred using:",
    "options": [
        "I filament winding",
        "Vacuum bag method",
        "Hand layup",
        "Resin transfer molding"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "I filament winding"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a defect in stone?",
    "options": [
        "Mottle",
        "Vent",
        "Shake",
        "Cleavage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cleavage"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "The term baluster is related to:",
    "options": [
        "Roof",
        "Stairs",
        "Floor",
        "Masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stairs"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "The outer curve of an arch is known as:",
    "options": [
        "Extrados",
        "Crown",
        "Skewback",
        "Spandrel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Extrados"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Temporary support given to unsafe structure is called:",
    "options": [
        "Jacking",
        "Shoring",
        "Underpinning",
        "Lifting"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Shoring"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "The members that support the roof covering materials of a sloped roof are called:",
    "options": [
        "Purlins",
        "Purlin cleats",
        "Patterns",
        "Rafters"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rafters"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "The end of a brick seen on the wall face (9x9 cm side) is called:",
    "options": [
        "Face",
        "Facing",
        "Header",
        "Closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "In stairs, a flyer is:",
    "options": [
        "The bottom part of the stair",
        "Molding under the tread",
        "A straight step with parallel width",
        "A projecting part of a step for support"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "A straight step with parallel width"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "A roof that slopes in four directions is called:",
    "options": [
        "Sloping roof",
        "Hip roof",
        "Gable roof",
        "Shed roof"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hip roof"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "In which type of bond are all bricks arranged in stretcher courses only?",
    "options": [
        "English bond",
        "Header bond",
        "Stretcher bond",
        "Flemish bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher bond"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "In which bond are all bricks arranged in header courses only?",
    "options": [
        "Header bond",
        "Flemish bond",
        "Dutch bond",
        "Facing bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header bond"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Which bond is considered the strongest in brickwork?",
    "options": [
        "English bond",
        "Raking bond",
        "Garden-wall bond",
        "Dutch bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "English bond"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "In which bond are headers distributed uniformly?",
    "options": [
        "Stretcher bond",
        "Flemish bond",
        "Header bond",
        "English bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flemish bond"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "In which bond is a header course provided after three or five stretcher courses?",
    "options": [
        "English cross bond",
        "Facing bond",
        "Raking bond",
        "Garden-wall bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Garden-wall bond"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "In which direction is a bonded brick laid with its length along the wall direction?",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Flemish",
        "Stretcher",
        "English"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "What should be avoided in brick masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Queen closer",
        "Brick bat",
        "Vertical joints",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vertical joints"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "In herringbone bond, bricks are laid at an angle to the line in which direction?",
    "options": [
        "60°, central",
        "60°, vertical",
        "45°, central",
        "45°, vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "45°, central"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "A portion of a brick cut into half-width is called:",
    "options": [
        "Half-split",
        "Half-closer",
        "Half-bed",
        "Half-bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Half-bat"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "What is placed at the beginning of each header course in English bond to avoid vertical joints?",
    "options": [
        "Queen closer",
        "Half-bat",
        "Three-quarter bat",
        "King closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "Bricks used at the corners of a building’s walls are called:",
    "options": [
        "Spalls",
        "Quoins",
        "Hearing",
        "Side"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quoins"
},
{
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Which bond includes one header course for every three or five stretcher courses?",
    "options": [
        "Dutch bond",
        "Zig-zag bond",
        "English garden-wall bond",
        "Facing bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "English garden-wall bond"
},
{
    "number": 33,
    "question": "Which IS code gives practice for brickwork?",
    "options": [
        "IS 2212",
        "IS 3102",
        "IS 3466",
        "IS 1077"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 2212"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "PVC flooring gives a:",
    "options": [
        "Matte finish",
        "Laminate",
        "Satin",
        "Natural"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Matte finish"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Glass flooring can be made using how many types of glass?",
    "options": [
        "5",
        "6",
        "3",
        "4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of brick flooring?",
    "options": [
        "Fireproof",
        "Cost-effective",
        "Slip-resistant",
        "Waterproof"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Waterproof"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The cheapest and best variety of marble flooring is:",
    "options": [
        "Albeto",
        "Makrana White",
        "Aranga",
        "Kumari"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Makrana White"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "How many types of floor tiles are available?",
    "options": [
        "3",
        "2",
        "4",
        "6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Mechanically produced carpet is a combination of:",
    "options": [
        "Rubber and synthetic fiber",
        "Wool and rubber",
        "Wool and synthetic fiber",
        "Rubber and natural fiber"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wool and synthetic fiber"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "The first step in flooring is:",
    "options": [
        "Topping",
        "Base coat",
        "Sand filling",
        "R.C.C. layer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Base coat"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Cork flooring is made from:",
    "options": [
        "Wood chips",
        "Cork pieces",
        "Wood fibers",
        "Bark of cork oak"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bark of cork oak"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "The cheapest and best variety of marble flooring is:",
    "options": [
        "Albeto",
        "Makrana White",
        "Aranga",
        "Kumari"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Makrana White"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "In suspended concrete floors, the beams used are:",
    "options": [
        "T-shaped",
        "Inverted L-shaped",
        "Inverted T-shaped",
        "I-shaped"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inverted T-shaped"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Upper floors are floating floors.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Which of the following utilities is not provided under a floor?",
    "options": [
        "Plumbing",
        "Soundproofing",
        "Air conditioning",
        "Gas lines"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gas lines"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Which of the following is a problem with ground floors?",
    "options": [
        "Cracks",
        "Stains",
        "Vibration",
        "Estimate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vibration"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Load distribution on the wall is not uniform in single joist timber floor.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Flooring used for spans more than 7.5 m is:",
    "options": [
        "Framed flooring",
        "Stone",
        "Glass",
        "Double joist timber"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Framed flooring"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "A floor has how many main parts?",
    "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "4",
        "5"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "A floor makes a sound when an intruder walks on it. This is called:",
    "options": [
        "Glass",
        "Chirping",
        "Sound",
        "Nightingale"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nightingale"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "The floor below the main floor is called:",
    "options": [
        "Plinth",
        "Sunken floor",
        "Sub-floor",
        "Hind floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sub-floor"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Which type of flooring is used in residential buildings?",
    "options": [
        "Ground timber floor",
        "Single joist timber floor",
        "Double joist timber floor",
        "Framed timber floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Single joist timber floor"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "With advancement in construction techniques, it is now possible to prepare flooring units:",
    "options": [
        "Precast",
        "On-site",
        "Factory-made",
        "In situ"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Precast"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "In flooring, hollow clay or concrete blocks are used to reduce the overall weight.",
    "options": [
        "Hollow block",
        "RCC",
        "Lapped",
        "Jack arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hollow block"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "In flooring, steel bars and concrete are used to form:",
    "options": [
        "Hollow block",
        "Precast concrete",
        "RCC",
        "Jack arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "RCC"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "In flooring, brick or cement concrete arches are constructed which rest on the lower flanges of light steel joists.",
    "options": [
        "Filler joist",
        "Precast concrete",
        "Jack arch",
        "Hollow block"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Jack arch"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "In flooring, small sections of rolled steel joists are embedded in concrete.",
    "options": [
        "Jack arch floor",
        "RCC floor",
        "Rib floor",
        "Filler joists"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Filler joists"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "In flooring, flagstones are used in two layers. This is called:",
    "options": [
        "Double flagstone floor",
        "Single flagstone floor",
        "Triple flagstone floor",
        "Filler joist timber floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Double flagstone floor"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "In flooring, intermediate supports provided in girders are called:",
    "options": [
        "Single joist timber floor",
        "Double joist timber floor",
        "Triple joist timber floor",
        "Tetra joist timber floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Triple joist timber floor"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "A floor in which single joists are placed below the floorboards is:",
    "options": [
        "Single joint timber floor",
        "Single joist timber floor",
        "Single timber floor",
        "Joist floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Single joist timber floor"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "In auditoriums for dancing or drama, which flooring is built at ground level?",
    "options": [
        "Composite floor",
        "Jack arch floor",
        "RCC floor",
        "Basement timber floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Basement timber floor"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "The other floors above ground level are known as:",
    "options": [
        "Roof",
        "Upper floor",
        "Lower floor",
        "Terrace"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Upper floor"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "The exposed surface of a floor is known as:",
    "options": [
        "Roof",
        "Floor",
        "Flooring",
        "Ceiling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flooring"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Binding materials used in mortar for plastering:",
    "options": [
        "Lime",
        "Cement",
        "Clay",
        "All of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of these"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Plastic mortar is obtained by mixing:",
    "options": [
        "Binding material, coarse aggregate, and water",
        "Fine aggregate and water",
        "Binding material, fine aggregate, and water",
        "Binding material and fine aggregate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Binding material, fine aggregate, and water"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Purpose of rendering is to protect exposed surfaces from:",
    "options": [
        "Rainwater penetration",
        "Moisture absorption",
        "Atmospheric agents like wind, snow",
        "All of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of these"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Plastering on an external exposed surface is called:",
    "options": [
        "Rendering",
        "Blending",
        "Rebranding",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rendering"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Fine hairline cracks on plastered surface are called:",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Crazing",
        "Braking",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Crazing"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "A common step of rectangular shape in plan is called:",
    "options": [
        "Flare",
        "Round-end step",
        "Splayed step",
        "Common step"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flare"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "The combination of tread and riser is called:",
    "options": [
        "Soffit",
        "String",
        "Waist",
        "Step"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Step"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "A step with one or both ends curved in plan is called:",
    "options": [
        "Bullnose step",
        "Balancing step",
        "Stepped step",
        "Common step"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Balancing step"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "The total horizontal length of a staircase in plan is called:",
    "options": [
        "Run",
        "Soffit",
        "Scotia",
        "Step"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Run"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "The projecting part of the tread beyond the riser is called:",
    "options": [
        "Pitch",
        "Rise",
        "Riser",
        "Nosing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nosing"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Horizontal platform between two flights of stairs is called:",
    "options": [
        "Landing",
        "Pitch",
        "Nosing",
        "Rise"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Landing"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Horizontal distance between two consecutive risers' faces is:",
    "options": [
        "Riser",
        "Flight",
        "Going",
        "Newel post"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Going"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "The vertical member fixed between railing and steps to support railing:",
    "options": [
        "Baluster",
        "Balustrade",
        "Flight",
        "Barrister"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Baluster"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Arrangement that enhances face appearance and reduces concrete usage:",
    "options": [
        "Rebated boot lintel",
        "D.P.C.",
        "RCC",
        "Reboot lintel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rebated boot lintel"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Standard concrete mix for RCC lintel (cement: sand: aggregate):",
    "options": [
        "1:2:3",
        "1:2:4",
        "1:4:8",
        "1:3:6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:2:4"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Reinforced cement concrete has replaced all other lintel materials:",
    "options": [
        "RCC lintels",
        "Wood lintels",
        "Stone lintels",
        "Timber lintels"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "RCC lintels"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Lintels made of steel angles or rolled steel joists:",
    "options": [
        "RCC lintels",
        "Steel lintels",
        "Wood lintels",
        "Timber lintels"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Steel lintels"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Lintels made of bricks usually placed on ends or edges:",
    "options": [
        "Stone lintels",
        "Brick lintels",
        "Wood lintels",
        "Timber lintels"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brick lintels"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Lintels made of stone slabs placed during openings:",
    "options": [
        "Stone lintels",
        "Brick lintels",
        "Steel lintels",
        "Wood lintels"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stone lintels"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "In timber lintels, depth should be about (with 80 mm min) span:",
    "options": [
        "1/6, 1/4",
        "1/12, 1/4",
        "1/12, 1/8",
        "1/6, 1/8"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1/12, 1/8"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Timber lintels are made of:",
    "options": [
        "Timber",
        "RCC",
        "Steel",
        "Brick"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Timber"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Currently, lintels widely used in structures for doors/windows:",
    "options": [
        "Timber",
        "Wood",
        "RCC",
        "Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "RCC"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "A horizontal member placed across openings to support above load:",
    "options": [
        "Door",
        "Window",
        "Sill",
        "Lintel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lintel"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Arches made of precast cement concrete blocks or monolithic concrete:",
    "options": [
        "Cement concrete arch",
        "Cement arch",
        "Concrete arch",
        "Rubble arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Concrete arch"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Arches made from bricks or soft, purpose-made bricks:",
    "options": [
        "Crushed arch",
        "Stone arch",
        "Brick arch",
        "Concrete arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brick arch"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Arches constructed with rubble or ashlar masonry:",
    "options": [
        "Stone arch",
        "Timber arch",
        "Brick arch",
        "Concrete arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stone arch"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Type of brick arch with finely cut bricks using wire saw:",
    "options": [
        "Wire cut arch",
        "Gauged arch",
        "Rough arch",
        "Saw cut arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gauged arch"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Type of arch made from bricks cut roughly into wedge shape with axe:",
    "options": [
        "Rough cut arch",
        "Rough arch",
        "Gauged arch",
        "Cut arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rough cut arch"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Type of arch made using ordinary uncut bricks:",
    "options": [
        "Rough arch",
        "Axed arch",
        "Rough cut arch",
        "Gauged arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rough arch"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Flat, segmental, semicircular, horse-shoe, and stilted are examples of:",
    "options": [
        "Two-centered arches",
        "Three-centered arches",
        "Five-centered arches",
        "One-centered arches"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "One-centered arches"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "A constructed structure is called:",
    "options": [
        "Brick masonry",
        "Stone masonry",
        "Brick and stone masonry",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stone masonry"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Why is mortar used in stone masonry work?",
    "options": [
        "To hold stones in place",
        "To form joints",
        "To fill hollow spaces",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "To strengthen the mortar in case of large voids, which component is added?",
    "options": [
        "Stone chippings",
        "Small size aggregates",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "More water"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Both (a) and (b)"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "In cement-lime mortar, which is the primary binding material?",
    "options": [
        "Lime",
        "Cement",
        "Both",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cement"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "In stone masonry, a horizontal layer of stones is known as:",
    "options": [
        "Bed",
        "Bond",
        "Stretcher",
        "Course"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Course"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The bottom surface of a stone where it rests is called:",
    "options": [
        "Face",
        "Back",
        "Support",
        "Bed"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bed"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "When stones are placed through the wall at regular intervals, it's called:",
    "options": [
        "Support",
        "Hearing",
        "Through stone",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Through stone"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "options": [
        "Plastering is costlier than pointing",
        "Pointing is costlier than plastering",
        "None are correct"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plastering is costlier than pointing"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Which of the following provides better protection against weathering?",
    "options": [
        "Plastering work",
        "Pointing work"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plastering work"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Mortar joints in masonry are first raked to a depth of approximately:",
    "options": [
        "5 mm",
        "8 mm",
        "13 mm",
        "17 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "13 mm"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "For lime mortar pointing, surface should be cured for at least:",
    "options": [
        "1 day",
        "2 days",
        "3 days",
        "10 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3 days"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "For cement mortar pointing, curing should last at least:",
    "options": [
        "3 days",
        "4 days",
        "7 days",
        "10 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 days"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Lime mortar for pointing is mixed in ratio:",
    "options": [
        "1:1",
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:1"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Cement mortar for pointing is mixed in ratio:",
    "options": [
        "1:1",
        "1:1.5",
        "1:2",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:2"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "In Recessed Pointing, the face of pointing mortar is kept:",
    "options": [
        "Horizontal",
        "Inside wall surface",
        "Sloped",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inside wall surface"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Recessed pointing face is kept:",
    "options": [
        "Horizontal",
        "Inside wall surface",
        "Sloped",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inside wall surface"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Cost estimation model that reflects the effect of economies of scale:",
    "options": [
        "Cost index model",
        "Segmenting model",
        "Per unit model",
        "Power sizing model"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Power sizing model"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Which is a fixed cost?",
    "options": [
        "Depreciation of assets",
        "Excise duty",
        "Advertisement cost",
        "Sales tax"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Advertisement cost"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Which model is used to update cost of power plant with same capacity?",
    "options": [
        "Per unit model",
        "Segmenting model",
        "Cost index model",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cost index model"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "IRC recommended camber for cement concrete roads:",
    "options": [
        "50 mm",
        "45 mm",
        "24 mm",
        "20 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "50 mm"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Land width needed for National and State highways in built-up areas:",
    "options": [
        "30 m to 60 m",
        "50 m to 70 m",
        "10 m to 16 m",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "30 m to 60 m"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Hot mix plant is used for:",
    "options": [
        "Cement concrete pavement",
        "Bituminous pavement",
        "Water-bound macadam",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bituminous pavement"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Scraper is used for:",
    "options": [
        "Scraping soil",
        "Only excavation",
        "Excavation, transport, and dumping",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Only excavation"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Power shovel size is governed by:",
    "options": [
        "Size of dipper",
        "Size of tires",
        "Engine power",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Size of dipper"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Sheep foot roller is used for:",
    "options": [
        "Soil",
        "Non-plastic silt",
        "Fine sand",
        "Clay soil"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Clay soil"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "If cement is used as binder in plaster, it is called:",
    "options": [
        "Lime plaster",
        "Cement plaster",
        "Mud plaster",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cement plaster"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Additives are used in mortar to improve:",
    "options": [
        "Adhesion",
        "Durability",
        "Workability",
        "All of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of these"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "In plastering mortar, fine aggregate passing through 150 micron sieve should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "3%",
        "5%",
        "7%",
        "10%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "5%"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Suitable type of water for plastering mortars is:",
    "options": [
        "Sea water",
        "River water",
        "Drinking water",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Drinking water"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Which stone is used for buildings in industrial cities?",
    "options": [
        "Marble slab",
        "Compact sandstone",
        "Gneiss",
        "Slate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compact sandstone"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Rubble masonry is divided into how many types?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "6",
        "10"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "6"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Random rubble masonry stones are:",
    "options": [
        "Dressed with chisel",
        "Dressed with hammer",
        "Dressed with axe",
        "Plain dressed"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dressed with chisel"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The nodules found in flint rubble are:",
    "options": [
        "Fly ash nodules",
        "Feldspar nodules",
        "Mica nodules",
        "Silica nodules"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Silica nodules"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "In arch masonry, which type of joint is used?",
    "options": [
        "Butt",
        "Table",
        "Rebated joint",
        "Dowel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rebated joint"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "What ratio of cement mortar is used for stone masonry?",
    "options": [
        "1:6",
        "1:3",
        "1:8",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:3"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Ashlar masonry uses:",
    "options": [
        "Dimension stones",
        "Polygonal stones",
        "Quarry dressed stones",
        "Square stones"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dimension stones"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Masonry that lies between rubble and ashlar types is:",
    "options": [
        "Rubble blocks in one course",
        "Ashlar rubble coursed",
        "Ashlar block in courses",
        "Rubble ashlar"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ashlar block in courses"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Which type of masonry requires highly skilled labor?",
    "options": [
        "Cut rubble",
        "Ashlar fine masonry",
        "Ashlar rough masonry",
        "Dry rubble masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dry rubble masonry"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Which of the following should not be followed in stone masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Dumbbell-shaped header stones",
        "Cure for 2–3 weeks",
        "Construction should be raised uniformly",
        "Stones used should be wet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dumbbell-shaped header stones"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "How many types of brick masonry are possible?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "5",
        "6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "A brick laid with its length along the direction of the wall is:",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Flemish",
        "Stretcher",
        "English"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "What should be avoided in brick masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Horizontal joints",
        "Queen closer",
        "Brick bat",
        "Vertical joints"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vertical joints"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Which bond looks better than English bond?",
    "options": [
        "Flemish",
        "Double Flemish",
        "Single Flemish",
        "Poly Flemish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Double Flemish"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Flemish bond is more expensive than English bond.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "In herringbone bond, bricks are laid at angles in both directions:",
    "options": [
        "60°, central",
        "60°, vertical",
        "45°, central",
        "45°, vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "45°, central"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "A part of a brick cut to half its width is:",
    "options": [
        "Half division",
        "Half closer",
        "Half bed",
        "Half bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Half bat"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "In English bond, what is used at the beginning of each header course to avoid vertical joints?",
    "options": [
        "Queen closer",
        "Half bat",
        "Three-fourth bat",
        "King closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Bricks used at corners of a structure are called:",
    "options": [
        "Spalls",
        "Quoins",
        "Hearing",
        "Side"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quoins"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "English garden wall bond includes 1 header course for every 3 or 5 stretcher courses:",
    "options": [
        "Dutch bond",
        "Zig-zag bond",
        "English Garden-wall bond",
        "Facing bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "English Garden-wall bond"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Which IS code gives practice guidelines for brickwork?",
    "options": [
        "IS 2212",
        "IS 3102",
        "IS 3466",
        "IS 1077"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 2212"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "How many main components are used to prepare concrete?",
    "options": [
        "5",
        "3",
        "2",
        "4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "The most common substitute for cement in concrete is:",
    "options": [
        "Slag",
        "Fly ash",
        "Bitumen",
        "Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bitumen"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Ideal water-cement ratio for hand mixing:",
    "options": [
        "0.4–0.5",
        "0.5–0.6",
        "0.6–1",
        "1.6–2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.5–0.6"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Which IS code provides details about water used in concrete?",
    "options": [
        "IS 456",
        "IS 383",
        "IS 565",
        "IS 3012"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 456"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "How many types of chemical admixtures are there?",
    "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "4",
        "5"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Retarders are used for:",
    "options": [
        "High-rise building construction",
        "Repair work",
        "Cold weather condition",
        "Grinding deep oil wells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Grinding deep oil wells"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "What is added to make white concrete?",
    "options": [
        "Fly ash",
        "Metakaolin",
        "Rice husk",
        "Pigment"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metakaolin"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "As water-cement ratio increases, which of the following also increases?",
    "options": [
        "Compressive strength",
        "Tensile strength",
        "Bleeding",
        "Workability"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Workability"
},
{
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Example of a plasticizer:",
    "options": [
        "Hydroxylated carboxylic acid",
        "Fluorosilicate",
        "Gypsum",
        "Surkhi"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydroxylated carboxylic acid"
},
{
    "number": 33,
    "question": "Which component in concrete provides compressive strength?",
    "options": [
        "Water",
        "Cement",
        "Aggregates",
        "Admixture"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aggregates"
},
{
    "number": 34,
    "question": "Mix ratio for M20 grade concrete is:",
    "options": [
        "1:3:6",
        "1:1.5:3",
        "1:1:2",
        "1:2:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:1.5:3"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Loss on Ignition (L.O.I.) refers to the weight loss of cement after heating at:",
    "options": [
        "1000 °C",
        "100 °C",
        "500 °C",
        "1500 °C"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1000 °C"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "On cooling below 1250 °C, C₃S (Tricalcium Silicate) decomposes:",
    "options": [
        "Rapidly",
        "Slowly",
        "Never",
        "Depends on conditions"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slowly"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "When sand is completely dried, its volume becomes:",
    "options": [
        "Equal",
        "Less",
        "More",
        "Cannot be said"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Equal"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "If the moisture content in sand is about 5–10% by weight, its bulking (increase in volume) is about:",
    "options": [
        "20%",
        "30%",
        "40%",
        "50%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "50%"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "If mineral oil is present in the concrete mix, it:",
    "options": [
        "Improves strength",
        "Reduces strength",
        "Increases workability",
        "Gives a smooth surface"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Improves strength"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "To neutralize 200 ml of a sample using Methyl Orange indicator, the amount of Normal HCl required should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "1 ml",
        "10 ml",
        "0.1 ml",
        "0.01 ml"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 ml"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "In a test with MgSO₄ solution, the loss of weight of a sample should not exceed (% Na₂SO₄, % MgSO₄):",
    "options": [
        "12%, 18%",
        "18%, 12%",
        "10%, 15%",
        "15%, 10%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "12%, 18%"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "In a Universal Testing Machine, for a specimen with circular cross-section, the gauge length is:",
    "options": [
        "3.65 √A",
        "4.65 √A",
        "5.65 √A",
        "6.65 √A"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "5.65 √A"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "In the compression test of cast iron, failure occurs by cracks appearing:",
    "options": [
        "Along the diagonal",
        "Parallel to the applied load",
        "Perpendicular to the applied load",
        "On the lateral side"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Along the diagonal"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "In the Brinell hardness test, the indenter used is a:",
    "options": [
        "Ball",
        "Cone",
        "Cylinder",
        "Pyramid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cone"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Which test is used to determine the dimensions of any object?",
    "options": [
        "Ultrasonic Test",
        "Torsion Test",
        "Eddy Current Test",
        "Compression Test"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Eddy Current Test"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "The Al₂O₃ (Alumina) content in fly ash is about:",
    "options": [
        "30–60%",
        "15–30%",
        "30%",
        "1–7%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15–30%"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "The property of a material which resists penetration or indentation by abrasion or scratching is called:",
    "options": [
        "Strength",
        "Hardness",
        "Stiffness",
        "Toughness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hardness"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "A Quality Management System improves customer perception of the company.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Wastage of good quality construction materials causes smooth functioning of the team to:",
    "options": [
        "Increase",
        "Decrease",
        "Not affect",
        "Give profit"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Decrease"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Job-site concrete handling, curing, sampling and testing process:",
    "options": [
        "Improves",
        "Deproves",
        "Recedes",
        "Worsens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Improves"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Reduces the cost of repair and maintenance of structures.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "The concrete mix should be designed in the laboratory using the materials that are actually used at the site.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "As per the recommendations of the Concrete Association of India, the minimum strength of blocks used in concrete masonry should be:",
    "options": [
        "3 N/mm²",
        "4 N/mm²",
        "2 N/mm²",
        "5 N/mm²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3 N/mm²"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "In concrete masonry, the core-void area of a hollow concrete block should not exceed _____ of the gross area.",
    "options": [
        "20%",
        "15%",
        "30%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "25%"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "In which type of surface finish are marble-like facing materials used on the front side of the block?",
    "options": [
        "Normal finish",
        "Glazed finish",
        "Special facing finish",
        "Coloured finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Special facing finish"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "During the manufacture of concrete masonry blocks, the cement–aggregate ratio should not be leaner than:",
    "options": [
        "1:6",
        "1:3",
        "3:4",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:6"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Which surface finish is mainly used for decorative works?",
    "options": [
        "Matt finish",
        "Coloured finish",
        "Special facing finish",
        "Glazed finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Glazed finish"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Solid concrete blocks are obtained from lightweight aggregates, while hollow concrete blocks are obtained from heavy aggregates.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "In solid masonry, hollow concrete units can be used for:",
    "options": [
        "Either load-bearing or non-load-bearing walls",
        "Only load-bearing walls",
        "Only non-load-bearing walls"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Either load-bearing or non-load-bearing walls"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "In concrete masonry, the cores of blocks are generally shaped as:",
    "options": [
        "Oval",
        "Square",
        "Triangular",
        "Circular"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Oval"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Which of the following is considered a rough surface finish?",
    "options": [
        "Glazed finish",
        "Coloured finish",
        "Special facing finish",
        "Grooved finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Grooved finish"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "In hollow clay block masonry, load-bearing main walls should be constructed using (cement : lime : sand) mortar in proportion:",
    "options": [
        "1:2:6",
        "1:1:6",
        "1:2:9",
        "1:1:9"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:1:6"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Hollow clay blocks provide good thermal insulation because of:",
    "options": [
        "Air trapped inside the block cells",
        "Air outside the block cells",
        "Resistance to water",
        "Resistance to air"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Air trapped inside the block cells"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a type of structural clay unit in hollow clay block masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Partition block",
        "Fixing block",
        "Load-bearing block",
        "Cavity block"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cavity block"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "In grooved tiles, the area covered by grooves should not exceed _____ of the total area of cored faces.",
    "options": [
        "20%",
        "30%",
        "40%",
        "50%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "50%"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "In hollow clay block masonry, the separation between cells is formed by:",
    "options": [
        "Webs",
        "Shells",
        "Grooves",
        "Blocks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Webs"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "The minimum average thickness of shells used in hollow clay block masonry should be:",
    "options": [
        "1 cm",
        "2 cm",
        "3 cm",
        "4 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2 cm"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Grooved tiles are used only in cases where plastering is to be done.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "In hollow clay block masonry, the minimum average thickness of webs should not be less than:",
    "options": [
        "1 cm",
        "2 cm",
        "3 cm",
        "4 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 cm"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Before use, all hollow clay blocks should be dipped in:",
    "options": [
        "Alcohol",
        "Acetone",
        "Water",
        "Ethane"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Reinforced brickwork is used in cases where:",
    "options": [
        "The wall carries very light loads",
        "The brickwork has to withstand shear stresses",
        "Longitudinal bonding needs to be reduced",
        "The wall is temporary"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "The brickwork has to withstand shear stresses"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Reinforced brickwork uses:",
    "options": [
        "First-class bricks with high compressive strength",
        "First-class bricks with medium compressive strength",
        "Second-class bricks with high compressive strength",
        "Second-class bricks with medium compressive strength"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "First-class bricks with high compressive strength"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Which type of sheet metal is cut and expanded to form a diamond mesh?",
    "options": [
        "Bricktor",
        "Pier",
        "Exmet",
        "Hoop iron"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Exmet"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "In reinforced brick masonry, reinforcement is placed:",
    "options": [
        "Only horizontally",
        "Horizontally and vertically"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Horizontally and vertically"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "In horizontal reinforcement, the number of hoop iron strips used per header brick is:",
    "options": [
        "One",
        "Two",
        "Three",
        "Four"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Two"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "In horizontal reinforcement, the number of hoop iron strips used per stretcher brick is:",
    "options": [
        "One",
        "Two",
        "Three",
        "Four"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "One"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Exmet is supplied in coil lengths of:",
    "options": [
        "80 m",
        "83 m",
        "85 m",
        "87 m"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "83 m"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "For embedding reinforcement in brick masonry, _____ is used.",
    "options": [
        "Lime mortar",
        "Cement concrete",
        "Dense cement mortar",
        "Lime concrete"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dense cement mortar"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Expansion of reinforcement joints results in:",
    "options": [
        "Expansion of joints",
        "Contraction of joints",
        "Shrinkage",
        "Tightening of joints"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Expansion of joints"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Based on the degree of workability and placing conditions, determine:",
    "options": [
        "Value of slump",
        "Maximum size of aggregate",
        "Quantity of mixing water",
        "Minimum water-cement ratio"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Value of slump"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Based on the economy and dimensions of the structure, determine:",
    "options": [
        "Value of slump",
        "Maximum size of aggregate",
        "Quantity of mixing water",
        "Minimum water-cement ratio"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Maximum size of aggregate"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "For a given slump and maximum size of coarse aggregate, determine:",
    "options": [
        "Value of slump",
        "Maximum size of aggregate",
        "Quantity of mixing water",
        "Minimum water-cement ratio"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quantity of mixing water"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Determined either from strength requirements or durability considerations is:",
    "options": [
        "Value of slump",
        "Maximum size of aggregate",
        "Quantity of mixing water",
        "Minimum water-cement ratio"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Minimum water-cement ratio"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "To determine the cement content in concrete, we consider:",
    "options": [
        "Slump value",
        "Maximum size of aggregate",
        "Quantity of mixing water",
        "Both maximum size of aggregate and quantity of mixing water"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Both maximum size of aggregate and quantity of mixing water"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The cement content required based on durability criteria should be:",
    "options": [
        "More",
        "Equal",
        "Less",
        "Not less"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Not less"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "The strength of concrete increases as the water-cement ratio (w/c) becomes:",
    "options": [
        "Lower",
        "Higher",
        "Poor",
        "Moderate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lower"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "The aim of a concrete mix designer should be to achieve optimum strength with cement content and workability that are:",
    "options": [
        "Maximum, non-acceptable",
        "Minimum, non-acceptable",
        "Maximum, acceptable",
        "Minimum, acceptable"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Minimum, acceptable"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "The maximum size of aggregate should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "1/5 of the minimum dimension of the structural member",
        "1/4 of the minimum dimension of the structural member",
        "1/3 of the minimum dimension of the structural member",
        "1/6 of the minimum dimension of the structural member"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1/5 of the minimum dimension of the structural member"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, the percentage of fly ash that can replace cement content is:",
    "options": [
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%",
        "30%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20%"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2002, the percentage of fly ash that can replace cement content is:",
    "options": [
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%",
        "30%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "25%"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, for OPC concrete with characteristic flexural strength of 4.5 N/mm², the minimum cement content shall not be less than:",
    "options": [
        "360 kg/m³",
        "425 kg/m³",
        "340 kg/m³",
        "500 kg/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "360 kg/m³"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, for PPC concrete with characteristic flexural strength of 4.5 N/mm², the minimum cement content shall not be less than:",
    "options": [
        "360 kg/m³",
        "425 kg/m³",
        "340 kg/m³",
        "500 kg/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "425 kg/m³"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, for OPC + Fly Ash mix concrete with characteristic flexural strength of 4.5 N/mm², the minimum cement content shall not be less than:",
    "options": [
        "360 kg/m³",
        "425 kg/m³",
        "340 kg/m³",
        "500 kg/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "340 kg/m³"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, the maximum free w/c ratio for OPC is:",
    "options": [
        "0.45",
        "0.40",
        "0.50",
        "0.55"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.45"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "As per IRC: 15–2011, the maximum free w/c ratio for PPC is:",
    "options": [
        "0.45",
        "0.40",
        "0.50",
        "0.55"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.50"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "IS code for specification of Ordinary Portland Cement (OPC) 33 Grade is:",
    "options": [
        "IS 269:1989",
        "IS 383:1970",
        "IS 455:1989",
        "IS 456:2000"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 269:1989"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "IS code for specification of coarse and fine aggregates from natural sources for concrete is:",
    "options": [
        "IS 269:1989",
        "IS 383:1970",
        "IS 455:1989",
        "IS 456:2000"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 383:1970"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "IS code for specification of Portland Slag Cement is:",
    "options": [
        "IS 269:1989",
        "IS 383:1970",
        "IS 455:1989",
        "IS 456:2000"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 455:1989"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "IS code for practice of plain and reinforced concrete (Code of Practice for Concrete) is:",
    "options": [
        "IS 269:1989",
        "IS 383:1970",
        "IS 455:1989",
        "IS 456:2000"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 456:2000"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "IS 457:1957 is the Code of Practice for:",
    "options": [
        "General construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Fly Ash based",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Calcined Clay based",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "General construction of plain and reinforced concrete for dams and other massive structures"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "IS 1489 (Part 1):1991 is the specification for:",
    "options": [
        "Code of practice for dams and massive structures",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Fly Ash based",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Calcined Clay based",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Fly Ash based"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "IS 1489 (Part 2):1991 is the specification for:",
    "options": [
        "Code of practice for dams and massive structures",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Fly Ash based",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Calcined Clay based",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement – Calcined Clay based"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "IS 1727:1967 is the standard for:",
    "options": [
        "Code of practice for dams and massive structures",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement",
        "Specification for Calcined Clay",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "IS 650:1991 specifies:",
    "options": [
        "Standard sand for testing cement",
        "Sampling and analysis of concrete",
        "Specification for Pozzolana cement",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Standard sand for testing cement"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "IS 1199:1959 specifies:",
    "options": [
        "Standard sand for testing cement",
        "Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete",
        "Specification for Portland Pozzolana Cement (Part 2 – Calcined Clay based)",
        "Methods of test for Pozzolanic materials"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Methods of sampling and analysis of concrete"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "A wall can be defined as a building component whose length is _____ times its thickness.",
    "options": [
        "Two",
        "Four",
        "Eight",
        "Sixteen"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Four"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "A column is a member that is:",
    "options": [
        "Vertical load-bearing",
        "Vertical non-load-bearing",
        "An isolated load-bearing",
        "An isolated non-load-bearing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "An isolated load-bearing"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Load-bearing walls are defined as walls that only carry their own weight, while non-load-bearing walls are defined as walls that, in addition to their own weight, can also carry superimposed loads.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Which type of wall is constructed to divide space inside a building?",
    "options": [
        "Partition wall",
        "Cavity wall",
        "Party wall",
        "Curtain wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Partition wall"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "A panel wall is:",
    "options": [
        "An internal non-load-bearing wall",
        "An external load-bearing wall",
        "An internal load-bearing wall",
        "An external non-load-bearing wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "An external non-load-bearing wall"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Cross-wall construction consists of internal walls running at _____ angles to the length of the building.",
    "options": [
        "Straight",
        "Acute",
        "Right",
        "Obtuse"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Right"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "A wall that separates adjoining buildings belonging to different owners is called:",
    "options": [
        "Party wall",
        "Isolated wall",
        "Cavity wall",
        "Partition wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Party wall"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "An isolated wall is defined as a wall that separates dwellings that are _____ buildings.",
    "options": [
        "Same, same",
        "Same, different",
        "Different, different",
        "Different, same"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Different, same"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a type of load-bearing wall?",
    "options": [
        "Solid masonry wall",
        "Panel wall",
        "Cavity wall",
        "Faced wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Panel wall"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "A curtain wall carries:",
    "options": [
        "Only vertical load",
        "Only lateral load",
        "Both vertical and lateral load",
        "Only its self-weight"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Only lateral load"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "A cavity wall is a wall consisting of _____ leaves.",
    "options": [
        "One",
        "Two",
        "Four",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Two"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "A faced wall is a type of load-bearing wall in which facing and backing are of the same material.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "In which type of load-bearing wall is the facing attached to the backing but not bonded?",
    "options": [
        "Veneered wall",
        "Cavity wall",
        "Faced wall",
        "Panel wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Faced wall"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "In a cavity wall, the space between leaves should be filled with:",
    "options": [
        "Waterproof material",
        "Load-bearing material",
        "Non-load-bearing material",
        "Insulating material"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Load-bearing material"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a type of load acting on wall structures?",
    "options": [
        "Dead load",
        "Black load",
        "Live load",
        "Earthquake load"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Black load"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Which of the following is not responsible for causing stress in a wall?",
    "options": [
        "Self-weight",
        "Weight of superimposed load",
        "Cement",
        "Lateral pressure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cement"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Live loads and dead loads act in a horizontal direction.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "In a masonry wall, the strength of mortar should be _____ than that of the masonry unit.",
    "options": [
        "Less",
        "More",
        "Equal",
        "Greater than or equal"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Less"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "In mortar mix, strength increases when it contains:",
    "options": [
        "Only lime",
        "Only cement",
        "More cement and less lime",
        "More lime and less cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "More lime and less cement"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Slenderness ratio of a wall does not depend on:",
    "options": [
        "Wall height",
        "Wall length",
        "Wall mass",
        "Wall thickness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wall mass"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Stability problem arises when the slenderness ratio is more than:",
    "options": [
        "30",
        "40",
        "50",
        "60"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "30"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "In the case of modular bricks, the actual thickness of a brick wall is:",
    "options": [
        "18 cm",
        "19 cm",
        "20 cm",
        "21 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "19 cm"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Slenderness ratio is inversely proportional to:",
    "options": [
        "Effective height",
        "Effective thickness",
        "Effective length",
        "Effective height and effective thickness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Effective height and effective thickness"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "The vertical side member of a shutter frame is called –",
    "options": [
        "Style",
        "Reveal",
        "Mullion",
        "Post"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Style"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The type of foundation generally used to support a heavy structure in sandy soil is –",
    "options": [
        "Combined footing",
        "Raft footing",
        "Pier footing",
        "Strap footing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pier footing"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "The bond in which every course consists of both headers and stretchers is –",
    "options": [
        "English bond",
        "Flemish bond",
        "Russian bond",
        "Mixed bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flemish bond"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "A portion of a brick cut to width is called –",
    "options": [
        "Closer",
        "Half-brick",
        "Bed",
        "Bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bat"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "The stone having the least crushing strength is –",
    "options": [
        "Granite",
        "Chalk",
        "Marble",
        "Slate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chalk"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Expansion joints in masonry walls are provided if length exceeds –",
    "options": [
        "10 m",
        "20 m",
        "30 m",
        "40 m"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "40 m"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Local swelling on the surface of finished plaster is called –",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Dubbing",
        "Blistering",
        "Hacking"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blistering"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "A floor made with 3 mm marble chips is called –",
    "options": [
        "Mosaic floor",
        "Terrazzo floor",
        "Chips floor",
        "Marble floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Terrazzo floor"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "A temporary rigid structure having platforms to enable masons to work at various stages of a building is called –",
    "options": [
        "Scaffolding",
        "Dead shore",
        "Raking shore",
        "Pinning"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scaffolding"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Black cotton soil is unsuitable for foundations because of –",
    "options": [
        "Low bearing capacity",
        "Uncertain permeability",
        "Homogeneous particles",
        "Large variation due to changes in moisture content"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Large variation due to changes in moisture content"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "The method in which each brick is laid with slight horizontal movement before being pressed into position with the brick hammer is called –",
    "options": [
        "Trowelling",
        "Laying",
        "Grouting",
        "Placing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Laying"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "In Jack Arch flooring, the rise is –",
    "options": [
        "1/6th of span",
        "1/8th of span",
        "1/10th of span",
        "1/12th of span"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1/12th of span"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "The outward slope of a verandah (corridor) is –",
    "options": [
        "1 in 40",
        "1 in 50",
        "1 in 60",
        "1 in 70"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 in 60"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "For a factory truss spanning 6 to 9 meters, the suitable type is –",
    "options": [
        "Mansard truss",
        "Queen post truss",
        "King post truss",
        "Collar truss"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "King post truss"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "A brick laid lengthwise along the wall face is called –",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "The under-surface of an arch is called –",
    "options": [
        "Soffit",
        "Intrados",
        "Haunch",
        "Back"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soffit"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "The crown is –",
    "options": [
        "The highest point on the extrados of an arch",
        "The highest point on the intrados of an arch",
        "The back of the arch",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "The highest point on the extrados of an arch"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "A soft pile with low resistance to flow of concrete is –",
    "options": [
        "Vibro pile",
        "Pressure pile",
        "Franki pile",
        "Pedestal pile"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vibro pile"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "The voussoir placed at the crown of an arch is called –",
    "options": [
        "Key",
        "Soffit",
        "Springer",
        "Haunch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Key"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "A brick laid widthwise along the wall face is called –",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "The inclined support at the ends of a stair string is called –",
    "options": [
        "Buster",
        "Header",
        "String",
        "Beam"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "String"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Choose the correct statement –",
    "options": [
        "Inclined borings are made to collect samples under existing structures",
        "Inclined borings are sometimes used instead of vertical holes",
        "The difference between inclined and vertical borings is maintained",
        "Inclined boring is vertically above the adjacent borehole"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inclined boring is vertically above the adjacent borehole"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Pile foundations are suitable for –",
    "options": [
        "Water-logged soils",
        "Soft rocks",
        "Compact soils",
        "Multi-storeyed buildings"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water-logged soils"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "In drilled pile holes, concrete compaction is done by compressed air in case of –",
    "options": [
        "Simplex pile",
        "Franki pile",
        "Pressure pile",
        "Vibro pile"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Franki pile"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "The triangular portion between crowns of two adjacent arches is called –",
    "options": [
        "Haunch",
        "Spandril",
        "Soffit",
        "Rise"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spandril"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "In horizontal DPC, thickness of cement concrete (1:2:4) is –",
    "options": [
        "2 cm",
        "4 cm",
        "6 cm",
        "8 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4 cm"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Borma boring is –",
    "options": [
        "The most primitive method of boring holes in the ground",
        "Usually used above water table in cohesive soils",
        "Used up to 5 m depth",
        "Most economical up to 5 m depth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Most economical up to 5 m depth"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "The foundation in which a strap beam connects two footings is called –",
    "options": [
        "Strip footing",
        "Strap footing",
        "Combined footing",
        "Raft footing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Strap footing"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "The offset from the base of wall to the edge of brickwork foundation is limited to –",
    "options": [
        "½ horizontal : 1 vertical",
        "⅔ horizontal : 1 vertical",
        "1 horizontal : 1 vertical",
        "2 horizontal : 1 vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2 horizontal : 1 vertical"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "A brick face measuring 9 cm × 9 cm as seen in wall face is generally called –",
    "options": [
        "Stretcher",
        "Face",
        "Front",
        "Header"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Quicklime reacts rapidly with water to form?",
    "options": [
        "Hydraulic Lime",
        "Slaked Lime",
        "Hydrated Lime",
        "Poor Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slaked Lime"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The component in lime that retards slaking action and increases hardness of setting is?",
    "options": [
        "Sulphate",
        "Alkalis",
        "Alumina"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sulphate"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "For underwater construction, which lime is used?",
    "options": [
        "Fat Lime",
        "Quick Lime",
        "Slaked Lime",
        "Hydraulic Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydraulic Lime"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Lime containing almost pure calcium oxide is called?",
    "options": [
        "Poor Lime",
        "Rich Lime",
        "Hydraulic Lime",
        "Limestone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rich Lime"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Eminent hydraulic lime contains silica, alumina and iron oxide in what percentage?",
    "options": [
        "5–10%",
        "10–25%",
        "25–30%",
        "30–40%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "25–30%"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Fat lime is—",
    "options": [
        "Slakes rapidly with high heat release",
        "Takes long time to develop strength",
        "Has high plasticity",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Fuel commonly used for burning limestone is?",
    "options": [
        "Coal",
        "Charcoal",
        "Firewood",
        "Any of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Any of the above"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Process of adding water to quicklime to convert it into hydrated lime is called?",
    "options": [
        "Calcination",
        "Hydration",
        "Slaking",
        "Burning"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slaking"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Adding Pozzolana (Surkhi) to lime helps in—",
    "options": [
        "Reducing shrinkage",
        "Increasing resistance to cracking",
        "Increasing resistance to moisture",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Lime mortar is prepared from—",
    "options": [
        "Quick Lime",
        "Fat Lime",
        "Lean Lime",
        "Hydraulic Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydraulic Lime"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Which is caustic lime?",
    "options": [
        "Quick Lime",
        "Fat Lime",
        "Milk of Lime",
        "Hydraulic Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quick Lime"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Quicklime obtained directly from kiln is called?",
    "options": [
        "Hydrated Lime",
        "Lump Lime",
        "Fat Lime",
        "Raw Limestone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lump Lime"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Which of the following is not used for production of fat lime?",
    "options": [
        "Oolitic Limestone",
        "Calcareous Tuff",
        "Marble",
        "Raw Limestone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Raw Limestone"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Lime that absorbs CO₂ from atmosphere is—",
    "options": [
        "Lean Lime",
        "Feebly Hydraulic Lime",
        "Rich Lime",
        "Fat Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lean Lime"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Lime used for finishing plaster is—",
    "options": [
        "Semi-hydraulic Lime",
        "Kankar Lime",
        "Magnesian Lime",
        "Eminently Hydraulic Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Magnesian Lime"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Hydraulic lime is obtained by burning—",
    "options": [
        "Oolitic Limestone",
        "Kankar",
        "Marble"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Kankar"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Quicklime is—",
    "options": [
        "Calcium Carbonate",
        "Calcium Oxide",
        "Pure product immediately after burning",
        "Lime quickly treated with water"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Calcium Oxide"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Lime commonly used in whitewashing is—",
    "options": [
        "Quick Lime",
        "Fat Lime",
        "Lean Lime",
        "Hydraulic Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat Lime"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Pozzolana in Portland cement provides advantages except—",
    "options": [
        "Low heat of hydration",
        "Increased shrinkage",
        "Reduced permeability",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Rate of hydration and hydrolysis of cement depends on—",
    "options": [
        "Soundness",
        "Fineness",
        "Setting time",
        "Tensile Strength"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fineness"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Expansion of Portland cement is tested by—",
    "options": [
        "Fineness Test",
        "Soundness Test",
        "Setting Time Test",
        "Normal Consistency Test"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soundness Test"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Specific surface of good Portland cement should not be less than (cm²/gm)?",
    "options": [
        "500",
        "1100",
        "2250",
        "3200"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2250"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Expansion of Portland cement occurs due to—",
    "options": [
        "Free Lime",
        "Magnesia",
        "Silica",
        "Both (b) & (c)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Magnesia"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Hydrated lime for mortar is prepared for—",
    "options": [
        "1 day",
        "3 days",
        "7 days",
        "14 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 day"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Interval between two coats of lime is—",
    "options": [
        "2–3 hours",
        "24 hours",
        "3 days",
        "7 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2–3 hours"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Cementing property of cement is due to—",
    "options": [
        "Lime",
        "Silica",
        "Iron Oxide",
        "Alumina"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lime"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "In good quality cement, the percentage of which compound should be higher?",
    "options": [
        "Silica",
        "Dicalcium Silicate",
        "Tricalcium Silicate",
        "Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tricalcium Silicate"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Initial setting of cement is due to—",
    "options": [
        "Dicalcium Silicate",
        "Tricalcium Silicate",
        "Tricalcium Aluminate",
        "Tetracalcium Aluminoferrite"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tricalcium Aluminate"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Fineness of cement is tested by—",
    "options": [
        "Air Permeability Method",
        "Le Chatelier Method",
        "Vicat Apparatus",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Air Permeability Method"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Vicat apparatus is used to determine—",
    "options": [
        "Initial setting time",
        "Final setting time",
        "Normal consistency",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "Expansion joint in Portland cement should not exceed—",
    "options": [
        "5 mm",
        "10 mm",
        "15 mm",
        "20 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 mm"
},
{
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Normal consistency of Portland cement is approximately—",
    "options": [
        "10%",
        "15%",
        "20%",
        "25%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "25%"
},
{
    "number": 33,
    "question": "Final setting time of ordinary cement should not be more than—",
    "options": [
        "2 hours",
        "4 hours",
        "8 hours",
        "10 hours"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 hours"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Dicalcium Silicate (C₂S):",
    "options": [
        "Hydrates rapidly",
        "Produces low heat of hydration",
        "Hardens quickly",
        "Has low resistance to sulphate attack"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Produces low heat of hydration"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Fineness of cement can be determined by sieve analysis using IS sieve No.?",
    "options": [
        "20",
        "10",
        "9",
        "6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "9"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "As cement sets and hardens, heat is produced. This is called—",
    "options": [
        "Heat of Hydration",
        "Latent Heat",
        "Heat of Evaporation",
        "Sensible Heat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Heat of Hydration"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Type of cement used in large dam construction?",
    "options": [
        "Blast Furnace Slag Cement",
        "Low Heat Cement",
        "Rapid Hardening Cement",
        "Ordinary Portland Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Low Heat Cement"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Most important compounds of cement are—",
    "options": [
        "C₃A and C₂S",
        "C₃S and C₃A",
        "C₃S and C₂S",
        "C₃A and C₄AF"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C₃A and C₄AF"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Fineness test of cement helps to estimate—",
    "options": [
        "Workability of mortar",
        "Heat of hydration",
        "Rate of hydration",
        "Durability of concrete"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rate of hydration"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Percentage of gypsum added in cement manufacture is—",
    "options": [
        "0.1–0.5%",
        "0.5–1%",
        "1–3%",
        "3–5%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1–3%"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "In manufacture of Portland cement, gypsum is added—",
    "options": [
        "During mixing",
        "During burning in rotary kiln",
        "At beginning of grinding clinker",
        "At the end of grinding clinker"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "At the end of grinding clinker"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Gypsum used in cement manufacturing acts as—",
    "options": [
        "Accelerator",
        "Air-entraining agent",
        "Plasticizer",
        "Retarder"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Retarder"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Cement type recommended for mass concrete work (like dams)?",
    "options": [
        "Ordinary Portland Cement",
        "Rapid Hardening Portland Cement",
        "Low Heat Cement",
        "Blast Furnace Slag Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Low Heat Cement"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Cement used for repair of large structures (like dams) requiring early strength is—",
    "options": [
        "OPC",
        "Low Heat Cement",
        "Rapid Hardening Cement",
        "Sulphate Resisting Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rapid Hardening Cement"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Gypsum (Plaster of Paris) is added during cement manufacture to—",
    "options": [
        "Increase strength",
        "Modify colour",
        "Reduce heat of hydration",
        "Control setting time"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Control setting time"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "To produce quick setting cement, which is added?",
    "options": [
        "Gypsum",
        "Alum",
        "Zinc Sulphate",
        "Aluminium Sulphate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aluminium Sulphate"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "High early strength of rapid hardening cement is due to—",
    "options": [
        "Higher gypsum content",
        "Burning at high temperature",
        "Finer grinding",
        "Higher C₃S (Tricalcium Silicate) content"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Higher C₃S (Tricalcium Silicate) content"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "High Alumina Cement is manufactured by fusing together—",
    "options": [
        "Limestone, Bauxite & Gypsum",
        "Limestone, Gypsum & Clay",
        "Limestone, Bauxite, Gypsum & Clay"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Limestone, Bauxite & Gypsum"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Cement most suitable for marine works?",
    "options": [
        "Low Heat Portland Cement",
        "Rapid Hardening Cement",
        "OPC",
        "Blast Furnace Slag Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blast Furnace Slag Cement"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Initial setting time of OPC is—",
    "options": [
        "10 min",
        "45 min",
        "30 min",
        "60 min"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "30 min"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "28-day compressive strength of cement is tested on 70.7 mm mortar cubes with ratio—",
    "options": [
        "1:6",
        "1:3",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:4"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "For 43 grade OPC, the 28-day compressive strength should be—",
    "options": [
        "43 MPa",
        "53 MPa",
        "43.5 MPa",
        "33 MPa"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "43 MPa"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Le-Chatelier method is used to test—",
    "options": [
        "Aggregates",
        "Aggregate fineness",
        "Soundness of Cement",
        "Compressive strength"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soundness of Cement"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Normal consistency test of cement is conducted using—",
    "options": [
        "Blaine Apparatus",
        "Le-Chatelier Apparatus",
        "Vane Apparatus",
        "Vicat Apparatus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vicat Apparatus"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "If standard consistency of cement is P, the water used for setting time test is—",
    "options": [
        "0.65 P",
        "0.85 P",
        "0.60 P",
        "0.78 P"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.85 P"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "First compound to react (set) in cement is—",
    "options": [
        "C₃S",
        "C₄AF",
        "C₃A",
        "C₂S"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C₃A"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Compound of cement that liberates maximum heat—",
    "options": [
        "C₃S",
        "C₄AF",
        "C₃A",
        "C₂S"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C₃A"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Bulk density of cement (1 bag) is about—",
    "options": [
        "1000 kg/m³",
        "1250 kg/m³",
        "1440 kg/m³",
        "1800 kg/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1440 kg/m³"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "To produce low heat cement, which compound is reduced?",
    "options": [
        "C₂S",
        "C₃A",
        "C₄AF"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C₃A"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Before setting test, cement must be tested for—",
    "options": [
        "Soundness",
        "Strength",
        "Fineness",
        "Consistency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Consistency"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Temperature range in cement kiln is—",
    "options": [
        "1000–1200 °C",
        "800–1000 °C",
        "1200–1500 °C",
        "1200–1300 °C"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1200–1300 °C"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Percentage of combined water required for full hydration of cement is about—",
    "options": [
        "15%",
        "23%",
        "38%",
        "40%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "23%"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Percentage of water required to fill voids in cement is about—",
    "options": [
        "13%",
        "15%",
        "18%",
        "23%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "15%"
},
{
    "number": 31,
    "question": "For full hydration of cement, required w/c ratio is—",
    "options": [
        "< 0.25",
        "0.25–0.35",
        "0.35–0.45",
        "0.45–0.65"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.35–0.45"
},
{
    "number": 32,
    "question": "Volume of one bag of cement is—",
    "options": [
        "0.0214 m³",
        "0.0434 m³",
        "0.0609 m³",
        "0.0347 m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "0.0347 m³"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "For an RCC slab, the concrete slump should be:",
    "options": [
        "0–25 mm",
        "25–50 mm",
        "75–100 mm",
        "50–125 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "75–100 mm"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Heaviest metal is:",
    "options": [
        "Steel",
        "Lead",
        "Tin",
        "Pig Iron"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lead"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Which of the following does not react with concrete?",
    "options": [
        "Sewage water",
        "Sulphuric acid",
        "Vegetable oil",
        "Alcohol"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alcohol"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Correct statement about lime types:",
    "options": [
        "Fat lime contains hardly 5% clay",
        "Hydraulic lime contains 5–30% clay",
        "Poor lime contains more than 30% clay",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat lime contains hardly 5% clay"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Initial temperature of concrete:",
    "options": [
        "–100°C",
        "–40°C",
        "100°C",
        "40°C"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "100°C"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Fuel commonly used to burn lime stone:",
    "options": [
        "Firewood",
        "Coal",
        "Charcoal",
        "Any of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Firewood"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Compound responsible for initial setting of cement:",
    "options": [
        "Tricalcium Aluminate",
        "Tricalcium Silicate",
        "Dicalcium Silicate",
        "Tetracalcium Aluminoferrite"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tricalcium Aluminate"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Approximate dry cement mortar required for brickwork:",
    "options": [
        "60%",
        "45%",
        "30%",
        "1%"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "30%"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Lime-cement mortar is also called:",
    "options": [
        "Mortar",
        "Gar-gated mortar",
        "Both (a) & (b)",
        "Lime mortar",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Both (a) & (b)"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Type of cement used:",
    "options": [
        "Ordinary Portland Cement",
        "Rapid Hardening Cement",
        "Sulphate Resisting Portland Cement",
        "Low Heat Cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sulphate Resisting Portland Cement"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Why lime is added in cement mortar:",
    "options": [
        "To increase setting time",
        "To increase workability",
        "To make it economical",
        "All of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "To increase workability"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Major disadvantage of using lime mortar:",
    "options": [
        "Sets slowly",
        "Fragrant",
        "Uneven",
        "Unsound"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sets slowly"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Lime mortar is usually made of:",
    "options": [
        "Pure lime",
        "Slaked lime",
        "Hydraulic lime",
        "Air-hardening lime",
        "Both (c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Both (c) & (d)"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Mortar after gauging should be used within:",
    "options": [
        "15 min",
        "30–60 min",
        "1–2 hours",
        "3–6 hours"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1–2 hours"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Composition of gauged mortar:",
    "options": [
        "Stone dust, sand, lime",
        "Lime, cement, sand",
        "Surkhi, lime, cement",
        "Sand, fly ash, cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lime, cement, sand"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Lime mortar mixture:",
    "options": [
        "Lime, cement, water",
        "Cement, sand, water",
        "Hydraulic lime, sand, water",
        "Air-hardening lime, sand, turpentine"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydraulic lime, sand, water"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Building mortars are classified into grades based on compressive strength:",
    "options": [
        "4 grade",
        "6 grade",
        "7 grade",
        "9 grade"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "9 grade"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Mortar for damp-proof courses and cement concrete roads:",
    "options": [
        "Lime mortar (1:2)",
        "Lime mortar (1:3)",
        "Cement mortar (1:2)",
        "Lime-cinder mortar (1:4)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cement mortar (1:2)"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Consumption of lime mortar after preparation:",
    "options": [
        "2 days",
        "14 days",
        "36 days",
        "36 hours"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "36 hours"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "X-ray protection mortar is a light mortar with bulk density less than 1500 kg/m³:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Small quantity of lime mortar is prepared by:",
    "options": [
        "Grinding",
        "Grilling",
        "Pounding",
        "Excavation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pounding"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Property not required for packing mortar used in oil wells:",
    "options": [
        "Must be water resistant",
        "Must have low uniformity",
        "Must resist water pressure",
        "Must form solid waterproof plug in rock voids"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Must have low uniformity"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Refractory mortar is obtained by addition of:",
    "options": [
        "Silica",
        "Sodium silicate",
        "Aluminium cement",
        "Caustic soda"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aluminium cement"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Process of adding cement to improve quality of lime mortar is called:",
    "options": [
        "Gaging",
        "Piling",
        "Slagging",
        "Re-bonding"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gaging"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Bulk density of heavy mortar is more than:",
    "options": [
        "500 kg/m³",
        "1000 kg/m³",
        "1500 kg/m³",
        "2500 kg/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1500 kg/m³"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Colour of sea sand:",
    "options": [
        "Blue",
        "Light brown",
        "Black",
        "Red"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Light brown"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Based on grain size, sand is classified into coarse, fine, and gravelly:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Increase in sand volume due to moisture is called:",
    "options": [
        "Bulking",
        "Normalization",
        "Shrinkage",
        "Titrating"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bulking"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Colour of river sand:",
    "options": [
        "Black",
        "Brown",
        "Grey",
        "White"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "White"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Lime mortar should be used after how long of its preparation?",
    "options": [
        "2 days",
        "14 days",
        "36 days",
        "36 hours"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "36 hours"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "How many types of brick masonry are possible?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "5",
        "6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Which of the following should NOT be followed in stone masonry construction?",
    "options": [
        "Header stones are dumbbell-shaped.",
        "Proper curing for 2–3 weeks.",
        "Construction should be raised evenly.",
        "Wet stones are used."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header stones are dumbbell-shaped."
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Laying which type of masonry requires great skill and efficient labor?",
    "options": [
        "Rubble masonry",
        "Ashlar fine masonry",
        "Ashlar masonry",
        "Dry rubble masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dry rubble masonry"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Masonry lies in an intermediate position between rubble and ashlar masonry. Which of the following describes it?",
    "options": [
        "Course with rubble sections",
        "Course with ashlar rubble",
        "Course with ashlar blocks",
        "Course with definite rubble columns"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Course with ashlar blocks"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Ashlar masonry uses:",
    "options": [
        "Dimension stones",
        "Polygonal stones",
        "Quarry-dressed stones",
        "Square stones"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dimension stones"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "What cement mortar ratio is used for stone masonry?",
    "options": [
        "1:6",
        "1:3",
        "1:8",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:3"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Which type of joint is used in arch masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Butt joint",
        "Table joint",
        "Rebate joint",
        "Dowel joint"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rebate joint"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Nodules of which material are found in flint stone rubble?",
    "options": [
        "Fly ash nodules",
        "Feldspar nodules",
        "Mica nodules",
        "Silica nodules"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Silica nodules"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "In random rubble masonry, the face stones are:",
    "options": [
        "Chisel-dressed",
        "Hammer-dressed",
        "Axe-dressed",
        "Plain"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chisel-dressed"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Rubble masonry is divided into how many types?",
    "options": [
        "4",
        "2",
        "6",
        "10"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "6"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Which stone is used in buildings located in industrial towns?",
    "options": [
        "Marble slab",
        "Compact sandstone",
        "Gneiss",
        "Slate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compact sandstone"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Which mortar can be used underwater?",
    "options": [
        "Hydraulic",
        "Pozzolana",
        "Lime",
        "Fly ash"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pozzolana"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Which material increases the setting speed of mortar?",
    "options": [
        "Lime",
        "Sulphur",
        "Pozzolana",
        "Gypsum"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lime"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Which is added to mortar to make it fireproof?",
    "options": [
        "Gypsum",
        "Asbestos cement",
        "Powdered glass",
        "Alumina cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alumina cement"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Bulk density of X-ray protective mortar is:",
    "options": [
        "6–12 kN/m³",
        "5 kN/m³ and above",
        "22 kN/m³ and above",
        "10–20 kN/m³"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "22 kN/m³ and above"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Packing mortar is used for:",
    "options": [
        "Oil wells",
        "Retaining walls",
        "Bricks",
        "Cracks in masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Oil wells"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Lightweight mortar is prepared using:",
    "options": [
        "Lime",
        "Surkhi",
        "Wood chips",
        "Fly ash"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wood chips"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "IS standard followed for mortar preparation is:",
    "options": [
        "IS 4455",
        "IS 2250-1981",
        "IS 3350-1981",
        "IS 5567"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 2250-1981"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Mortar ratio used for works is:",
    "options": [
        "1:3–1:4",
        "1:2–1:3",
        "1:7–1:8",
        "1:5–1:6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:2–1:3"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "MM 1.5 means:",
    "options": [
        "1.5 bags of cement in masonry mortar",
        "1.5 bags of cement in light mortar",
        "Compressive strength of 1.5 N/mm² in masonry mortar",
        "Compressive strength of 1.5 N/mm² in light mortar"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compressive strength of 1.5 N/mm² in masonry mortar"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Primary use of cement mortar (PCM) is:",
    "options": [
        "Repairing concrete structures",
        "Stone masonry",
        "Tile masonry",
        "Brick masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Repairing concrete structures"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "The first used mortar was:",
    "options": [
        "Lime mortar",
        "Mud mortar",
        "Cement",
        "Organic mortar"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mud mortar"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "The word “mortar” is derived from Latin:",
    "options": [
        "Mortarium",
        "Mortar",
        "Mortorium",
        "Mortorim"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mortorim"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Which of the following is a tool used in masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Plumb bob",
        "Saw",
        "Bending lever",
        "Bonding hook"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plumb bob"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Identify the tool:",
    "options": [
        "Straight edge",
        "Spirit level",
        "Spade",
        "Plumb bob"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Straight edge"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Before masonry, the surface is wetted for better quality with:",
    "options": [
        "Potable water",
        "Mortar",
        "Lime water",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lime water"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Why is the surface wetted before brickwork?",
    "options": [
        "To prevent absorption of water from mortar by the ground",
        "To clean the surface",
        "To spread mortar easily",
        "To gain strength"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "To prevent absorption of water from mortar by the ground"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "How do you prepare the surface before masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Remove debris",
        "Clean with wire brush",
        "Remove loose concrete",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Level transfer is done with the help of:",
    "options": [
        "Water level pipe",
        "Plumb bob",
        "Spirit level",
        "Straight edge"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water level pipe"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Identify the level-checking tool:",
    "options": [
        "Spirit level",
        "Straight edge",
        "Water level pipe",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spirit level"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Why should the brick level be checked in each course?",
    "options": [
        "For proper thickness of masonry",
        "For proper level",
        "For proper vertical alignment",
        "For good appearance"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "For proper level"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Which quality of sand should be used in brick masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Well-graded",
        "Coarse sand",
        "Fine sand",
        "Any of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fine sand"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Why are bricks soaked in water before laying?",
    "options": [
        "So they do not absorb water from mortar",
        "To gain more strength",
        "To improve durability",
        "To look better"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "So they do not absorb water from mortar"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "In which condition should a brick be cut using a mason’s trowel?",
    "options": [
        "When the brick is soft",
        "When the brick is hard",
        "When the brick is large"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "When the brick is large"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Horizontal alignment in masonry is checked by:",
    "options": [
        "Mason’s line",
        "Straight edge",
        "Plumb bob",
        "Spirit level"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spirit level"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Vertical alignment in masonry is checked with:",
    "options": [
        "Plumb bob",
        "Mason’s line",
        "Spirit level",
        "Straight edge"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plumb bob"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Identify the working action shown in the picture:",
    "options": [
        "Checking vertical alignment",
        "Checking level",
        "Checking horizontal alignment",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Checking level"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Why is curing important for brick masonry?",
    "options": [
        "To maintain water–cement ratio",
        "To maintain strength",
        "To maintain cement bonding",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "When should curing be done in masonry?",
    "options": [
        "At each stage where cement is used",
        "After masonry dries",
        "After work completion",
        "After 3 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "At each stage where cement is used"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Masonry levels are checked with:",
    "options": [
        "Spirit level in every course",
        "Plumb bob in every course",
        "Mason’s line in every course",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spirit level in every course"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Vertical alignment in masonry is checked with the help of:",
    "options": [
        "Plumb bob",
        "Spirit level",
        "Thread",
        "Straight edge"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plumb bob"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Horizontal lines are checked with:",
    "options": [
        "Mason’s line",
        "Spirit level",
        "Plumb bob",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mason’s line"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "A straight edge is also used for checking:",
    "options": [
        "Line alignment",
        "Roughness",
        "Wall length",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Roughness"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "A straight edge is generally made of:",
    "options": [
        "Aluminium",
        "Copper",
        "Steel",
        "Steel–aluminium alloy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aluminium"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Identify the tool in the picture:",
    "options": [
        "Tri-square",
        "Right angle",
        "90° angle",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tri-square"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "The main use of a tri-square is:",
    "options": [
        "To check right angles at corners",
        "To mark 45° angles",
        "To mark 180° lines",
        "To mark 30° angles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "To check right angles at corners"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Why is proper alignment important in masonry for stairs?",
    "options": [
        "To avoid problems during railing fixing",
        "To avoid problems during steel fixing",
        "To avoid problems during concreting",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "What is dampness in masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Groundwater at base",
        "Water seepage",
        "Swelling",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water seepage"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "How do you reinstall a brick/block piece into masonry?",
    "options": [
        "Clean the part, wet it with water, and fix with rich cement mortar",
        "Clean the part, wet with water, and fix with rich lime mortar",
        "Both A & B",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Clean the part, wet it with water, and fix with rich cement mortar"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "What precaution should be taken while repairing an old surface?",
    "options": [
        "Loose particles and dust should be cleaned",
        "Surface should be properly dry",
        "Only loose particles should be cleaned",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Loose particles and dust should be cleaned"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "What is the first step before plastering?",
    "options": [
        "Read the drawing",
        "Arrange labour",
        "Repair brick masonry",
        "Take work permit"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Repair brick masonry"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Tools used in plastering include:",
    "options": [
        "Spirit level",
        "Jointer",
        "Mason’s trowel",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Tri-square is used in plastering to check:",
    "options": [
        "Right angle at corners",
        "Thickness of plaster",
        "Sand particles",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Right angle at corners"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Ordinary concrete can be made waterproof by adding:",
    "options": [
        "Pudlo",
        "Impermo",
        "Snosem",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The opening given parallel to the roof surface in a sloping roof is called:",
    "options": [
        "Dormer window",
        "Skylight window",
        "Lantern window",
        "Louvered window"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Skylight window"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "Mortar in which both cement and lime are used as binding materials is called:",
    "options": [
        "Cement mortar",
        "Lime mortar",
        "Fire-resistant mortar",
        "Grounded mortar"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Grounded mortar"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "To stagger vertical joints in consecutive courses of a wall, a piece of brick used at the end of a course is called:",
    "options": [
        "Bat",
        "Header",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Closer"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Vertical sides of a door or window opening in a wall are called:",
    "options": [
        "Work area",
        "Reveal",
        "Jamb",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Jamb"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Type of ashlar masonry with finely chiselled stones and joint thickness not exceeding 3 mm:",
    "options": [
        "Chamfered ashlar masonry",
        "Facing ashlar masonry",
        "Random polygonal ashlar masonry",
        "Ashlar masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ashlar masonry"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Height of a building is measured:",
    "options": [
        "Between roof and ground level",
        "Between roof and floor level",
        "Roof above ground level",
        "Ground to roof"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Between roof and floor level"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Highest line of a sloping roof where two opposite slopes meet is called:",
    "options": [
        "Hip",
        "Ridge",
        "Crown",
        "Eave"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ridge"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Recommended slope for a flat RCC roof is:",
    "options": [
        "Zero",
        "Few degrees",
        "10°",
        "20°"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Few degrees"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Lower edge of a pitched roof from where rainwater falls off is called:",
    "options": [
        "Hip",
        "Gable",
        "Ridge",
        "Eaves"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Eaves"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Arches with more than four centers in masonry are called:",
    "options": [
        "Two-centered arches",
        "Gothic arches",
        "Ogee arches",
        "Drop Gothic arches"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ogee arches"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Line of intersection of two surfaces of a sloping roof forming an internal angle less than 180° is called:",
    "options": [
        "Ridge",
        "Hip",
        "Valley",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Valley"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Stone with maximum crushing strength is:",
    "options": [
        "Granite",
        "Chalk",
        "Slate",
        "Sandstone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Granite"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Brick-nogging type partition wall is constructed by:",
    "options": [
        "Laying bricks as stretchers in cement mortar",
        "Laying bricks as headers in cement mortar",
        "Reinforcing brick wall with iron strips",
        "Brickwork within a wooden framework"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brickwork within a wooden framework"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Depth of lean concrete bed at the base of a wall is:",
    "options": [
        "10 cm",
        "15 cm",
        "Equal to the projection of the wall foundation",
        "Less than the projection of the wall foundation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Equal to the projection of the wall foundation"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Construction joints in buildings are generally provided after:",
    "options": [
        "10 m",
        "15 m",
        "20 m",
        "40 m"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "40 m"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "A piece of brick cut at the width’s center to match the full length of a brick is called:",
    "options": [
        "Half brick",
        "Queen closer",
        "King closer",
        "Bevelled closer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Queen closer"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Type of arch used in high-class buildings where appearance is important is called:",
    "options": [
        "Ashlar arch",
        "Rubble arch",
        "Gauged brick arch",
        "Excised brick arch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ashlar arch"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "A 19 cm × 9 cm side of a brick as seen in a wall face is called:",
    "options": [
        "Stretcher",
        "Face",
        "Front",
        "Header"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Typical thickness of a reinforced brick partition wall is:",
    "options": [
        "5 cm",
        "10 cm",
        "15 cm",
        "20 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 cm"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Stone masonry laid in fine stones in cement or lime is:",
    "options": [
        "Random rubble masonry",
        "Coursed rubble masonry",
        "Dry rubble masonry",
        "Ashlar masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ashlar masonry"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Cement-sand mortar ratio for plastering exposed brick walls should be:",
    "options": [
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:4",
        "1:6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:4"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Steps used to change the direction of stairs are called:",
    "options": [
        "Round steps",
        "Angular steps",
        "Winders",
        "Radial steps"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Winders"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "In arch construction, the sand-box method is used for:",
    "options": [
        "Centering",
        "Actual laying of arch work",
        "Striking the centering",
        "None of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Striking the centering"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Foundation is placed below ground level for:",
    "options": [
        "Strength",
        "Workability",
        "Structural stability",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Structural stability"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Bond type in brickwork where alternate courses of stretcher and header are used:",
    "options": [
        "Flemish bond",
        "English bond",
        "Stretcher bond",
        "Header bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "English bond"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Width of hollow space between two walls of cavity wall should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "5 cm",
        "7.5 cm",
        "10 cm",
        "15 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 cm"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Type of stone masonry in which stones of uniform height are laid in courses is:",
    "options": [
        "Random rubble masonry",
        "Coursed rubble masonry",
        "Uncoursed masonry",
        "Ashlar masonry"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Coursed rubble masonry"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Concrete is used for constructing walls and roofs for:",
    "options": [
        "Heat-proof",
        "Sound-proof",
        "Neither (a) nor (b)",
        "Both (a) and (b)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Both (a) and (b)"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Depth of concrete bed of foundation depends on:",
    "options": [
        "Projection of concrete block above it",
        "Soil pressure above it",
        "Concrete mix",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "The depth of excavation is usually measured using:",
    "options": [
        "Ranging rod",
        "Steel tape",
        "Leveling staff",
        "Boning rod"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Boning rod"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "A 9 cm × 9 cm side of a brick as seen on the wall face is called:",
    "options": [
        "Stretcher",
        "Face",
        "Front",
        "Header"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "The projection limit from the foundation wall to the outer end for brickwork is:",
    "options": [
        "1/2 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "2/3 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "1 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "2 horizontal to 1 vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 horizontal to 1 vertical"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Exposed vertical parts at right angles on a door or window frame are called:",
    "options": [
        "Jamb",
        "Lintels",
        "Reveal",
        "Soffits"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Reveal"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Projections at the head of a door or window frame are called:",
    "options": [
        "Transoms",
        "Horns",
        "Stops",
        "Choke"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Horns"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The line of intersection of sloping roof surfaces with an external angle greater than 180° is called:",
    "options": [
        "Ridge",
        "Hip",
        "Valley",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ridge"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Distance between the depth of an arch:",
    "options": [
        "Ground level and springing line",
        "Crown and springing line",
        "Crown and ground level",
        "Intrados and extrados"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Intrados and extrados"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "In brick walls, expansion joints are made greater than nominal thickness by:",
    "options": [
        "5 mm",
        "10 mm",
        "15 mm",
        "20 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20 mm"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Precast concrete beams should not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "1 cm per meter length",
        "2 cm per meter length",
        "4 cm per meter length",
        "5 cm per meter length"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2 cm per meter length"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "In multistorey buildings, the first forms removed are those of:",
    "options": [
        "Beams and girders",
        "Column forms",
        "Bottom beams and girders",
        "All above simultaneously"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Beams and girders"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "If a building’s first-floor height is 3.2 m and riser is 13 cm, the required number of steps is:",
    "options": [
        "12",
        "18",
        "24",
        "25"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "24"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Dado is generally provided in:",
    "options": [
        "Dining hall",
        "Bathroom",
        "Living room",
        "Verandah"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bathroom"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "A roof sloping in four directions is called:",
    "options": [
        "Shed roof",
        "Gable end roof",
        "Hipped roof",
        "Gambrel roof"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hipped roof"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "External angle between outer faces of a wall is called:",
    "options": [
        "Turn",
        "Junction",
        "Quoin",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Quoin"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Minimum thickness of walls in a single-storey building constructed with 1:6 cement mortar:",
    "options": [
        "10 cm",
        "15 cm",
        "20 cm",
        "25 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "20 cm"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Lower half of the area between the crown and the sloping back of an arch is called:",
    "options": [
        "Spandrel",
        "Hunch",
        "Springing",
        "Soffit"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hunch"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Couple roof is used for span:",
    "options": [
        "3.5 m or less",
        "3.5–5 m",
        "5–6.5 m",
        "6.5–8 m"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3.5 m or less"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Recommended solid slope for beams and slabs:",
    "options": [
        "25–50 mm",
        "25–75 mm",
        "30–125 mm",
        "50–100 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "30–125 mm"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Pile foundation is generally provided if soil is:",
    "options": [
        "Compacted",
        "Water-logged",
        "Man-made",
        "All of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Pile with a bulb filled with concrete at its lower end is called:",
    "options": [
        "Simplex pile",
        "Mac-Arthur pile",
        "Raymond pile",
        "Franki pile"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mac-Arthur pile"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Decorative sloped course placed on top of a wall is called:",
    "options": [
        "Corbelling",
        "Coping",
        "Frieze",
        "Lintel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Corbelling"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Cut in a door frame to receive a shutter is called:",
    "options": [
        "Louver",
        "Stop",
        "Horn",
        "Rebate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rebate"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Lime-sand mortar ratio used for brickwork:",
    "options": [
        "1:1",
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:2"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "For a 10 cm thick partition wall, preferred bond is:",
    "options": [
        "English bond",
        "Flemish bond",
        "Header bond",
        "Stretcher bond"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher bond"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Strength of brick masonry in 1:6 cement mortar:",
    "options": [
        "20 ton/m²",
        "40 ton/m²",
        "50 ton/m²",
        "60 ton/m²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "50 ton/m²"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "When designing stairs, the product of rise and run is approximately:",
    "options": [
        "350",
        "420",
        "450",
        "500"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "420"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Process of roughening the backing surface before plastering:",
    "options": [
        "Dubbing",
        "Hacking",
        "Blistering",
        "Peeling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hacking"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Window provided on a sloping roof is called:",
    "options": [
        "Lantern window",
        "Dormer window",
        "Louver window",
        "Rash window"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dormer window"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Nominal thickness of a brick wall in mm:",
    "options": [
        "90 mm",
        "150 mm",
        "190 mm",
        "200 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "200 mm"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Mud plaster does not require curing.",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a type of plaster finish?",
    "options": [
        "Rough-cast",
        "Pebble-dash",
        "Sand-faced",
        "Wood"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wood"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "In a lime-cement plaster with a ratio of 1:1:6, the composition is:",
    "options": [
        "Lime : Cement : Sand",
        "Cement : Lime : Sand",
        "Lime : Sand : Gravel",
        "Cement : Sand : Gravel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cement : Lime : Sand"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "A wooden surface requires how many plaster coats?",
    "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "1",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Tool used to press and evenly spread mortar:",
    "options": [
        "Trowel",
        "Aluminium rod",
        "Floats",
        "Brush"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Floats"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "In plastering, the first coat is called, with thickness in mm:",
    "options": [
        "Undercoat, 6-9",
        "Floating coat, 6-9",
        "Floating coat, 10-15",
        "Undercoat, 10-15"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Undercoat, 10-15"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Based on materials, which is not a type of plaster?",
    "options": [
        "Cement",
        "Gypsum",
        "Pozzolana",
        "Lime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pozzolana"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Which IS code specifies the requirements for cement plaster?",
    "options": [
        "IS 1500",
        "IS 1221",
        "IS 1400",
        "IS 1661"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IS 1661"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Before plastering, the surface must be:",
    "options": [
        "Rough",
        "Smooth",
        "Cemented",
        "Wet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rough"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Ensures uniform thickness of plaster:",
    "options": [
        "Bull point",
        "Pivot point",
        "Bull mark",
        "Bench mark"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bull mark"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Plaster is also called:",
    "options": [
        "Pre-casting",
        "Parging",
        "Porting",
        "Polishing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Parging"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "For supporting a heavy structure on sandy soil, the commonly used foundation type is:",
    "options": [
        "Combined footing",
        "R.F. footing",
        "Pier footing",
        "Strap footing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pier footing"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Stone with the lowest crushing strength:",
    "options": [
        "Granite",
        "Chalk",
        "Marble",
        "Sandstone"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chalk"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Brick laid across the width is called:",
    "options": [
        "Closer",
        "Half brick",
        "Bed",
        "Bat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bat"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Floor made with 3mm marble chips is called:",
    "options": [
        "Mosaic floor",
        "Terrazzo floor",
        "Chip floor",
        "Marble floor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Terrazzo floor"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Local swelling in finished plaster is called:",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Dubbing",
        "Blistering",
        "Hacking"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blistering"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "Expansion joints are provided in masonry walls if length exceeds:",
    "options": [
        "10 m",
        "20 m",
        "30 m",
        "40 m"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "40 m"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Method of placing each brick with a small horizontal gap before pressing it with a brick hammer:",
    "options": [
        "Trolling",
        "Laying",
        "Retaining",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Laying"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Unsuitable due to large variations in properties caused by moisture content:",
    "options": [
        "Low impact strength",
        "Uncertain permeability",
        "Particle uniformity",
        "Large property change due to moisture"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Large property change due to moisture"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Brick laid parallel to the wall face along its length is called:",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer",
        "None of these"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stretcher"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "Type of truss for a factory with span 6–9 m:",
    "options": [
        "Mansard truss",
        "Queen post truss",
        "King post truss",
        "Collar truss"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Not provided"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Slope:",
    "options": [
        "1 in 40",
        "1 in 50",
        "1 in 60",
        "1 in 70"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 in 60"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Inclined support at stair edges and rising ends is called:",
    "options": [
        "Buster",
        "Header",
        "String",
        "Beam"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "String"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Brick laid parallel to the wall face along its width is called:",
    "options": [
        "Header",
        "Stretcher",
        "Closer",
        "None"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Header"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Stone placed on the crown of an arch is called:",
    "options": [
        "Keystone",
        "Soffit",
        "Springer",
        "Corbel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Keystone"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Triangular portion between two adjacent arches and their crowns is called:",
    "options": [
        "Hunch",
        "Spandrel",
        "Soffit",
        "Rise"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spandrel"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "In drilled pile holes, concrete compaction is done by compressed air in case of:",
    "options": [
        "Simplex pile",
        "Franki pile",
        "Pressure pile",
        "Vibro pile"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pressure pile"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Pile foundations are suitable for:",
    "options": [
        "Water-logged soil",
        "Soft rocks",
        "Compact soil",
        "Multistorey buildings"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water-logged soil"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Foundation with a cantilever beam joining two footings is called:",
    "options": [
        "Strip footing",
        "Strap footing",
        "Combined footing",
        "Raft footing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Strap footing"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "Thickness of horizontal D.P.C. using cement concrete:",
    "options": [
        "2 cm",
        "4 cm",
        "6 cm",
        "8 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "4 cm"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "Parian cement plaster is obtained when POP is calcined with:",
    "options": [
        "Pearl ash",
        "Alum",
        "Borax",
        "Petroleum"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Borax"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The detachment of plaster from the background is called:",
    "options": [
        "Peeling",
        "Plastering",
        "Distempering",
        "Graining"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Peeling"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "The white crystalline substance that appears on the surface of plaster due to salts in the material is called:",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Crystallization",
        "Efflorescence",
        "Crazing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Efflorescence"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "The first coat of applied plaster is the undercoat:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "A thin layer of cement particles formed due to excessive flow is called:",
    "options": [
        "Undercoat",
        "Peel",
        "Latence",
        "Latch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Latence"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "The process of roughening the background is called:",
    "options": [
        "Hacking",
        "Plastering",
        "Painting",
        "Soaking"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hacking"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "Wooden strips fixed on the surface for applying the first coat of plaster are called:",
    "options": [
        "Hooks",
        "Grounds",
        "Pins",
        "Bars"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Grounds"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "The term for mixing various plaster components is called:",
    "options": [
        "Flaking",
        "Blooming",
        "Gaging",
        "Hacking"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gaging"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Distant patches on the previous coat of plaster are called scaling:",
    "options": [
        "Flaking",
        "Disturbing",
        "Painting",
        "Smiling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flaking"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "The final coat of plaster is called:",
    "options": [
        "Background",
        "Finishing coat",
        "Undercoat",
        "Plastered coat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Finishing coat"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Filling hollow spaces left in solid backgrounds is called:",
    "options": [
        "Dubbing",
        "Hugging",
        "Smiling",
        "Painting"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dubbing"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Small plaster markers placed on the background to set levels are called:",
    "options": [
        "Patches",
        "Balls",
        "Dots",
        "Points"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dots"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "The top part of a dead plastered wall:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Development of hairline cracks is called:",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Dubbing",
        "Crazing",
        "Abrasion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Crazing"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Development of fissures in plaster due to background movement is called:",
    "options": [
        "Cracking",
        "Peeling",
        "Hacking",
        "Smiling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cracking"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "Swelling on a finished plaster surface is called:",
    "options": [
        "Dots",
        "Blistering",
        "Dubbing",
        "Smiling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blistering"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "The surface on which the first coat of plaster is applied is called:",
    "options": [
        "Dado",
        "Dot",
        "Background",
        "Face"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Background"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Keene’s cement is obtained by slaking cement with pigment in glue:",
    "options": [
        "Siripet",
        "Scagliola",
        "Snowcrete",
        "Colorecret"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scagliola"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Cement obtained by slaking alum with Plaster of Paris is:",
    "options": [
        "Parian cement",
        "Martin cement",
        "Keene cement",
        "Colorecat cement"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Keene cement"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "Used as a final coat for X-ray rooms:",
    "options": [
        "Gypsum plaster",
        "Barium plaster",
        "Granite plaster",
        "Marble plaster"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Barium plaster"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "A mixture of finely crushed marble, mica, and cement is called:",
    "options": [
        "Granite silicon plaster",
        "Barium plaster",
        "Asbestos marble plaster",
        "Acoustic plaster"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Asbestos marble plaster"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "Surface prepared for acoustic treatment of hall or room:",
    "options": [
        "Acoustic plaster",
        "Marble plaster",
        "Barium plaster",
        "Gypsum plaster"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Acoustic plaster"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Sometimes observed on plastered surfaces, especially when plaster is applied on metal rods:",
    "options": [
        "Rust stains",
        "Uneven surface",
        "Popping",
        "Peeling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Uneven surface"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Conical holes on plastered surfaces are caused by:",
    "options": [
        "Popping",
        "Rust stains",
        "Softness",
        "Uneven surface"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Popping"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Plaster peeling off some parts of the surface forming patches is called:",
    "options": [
        "Popping",
        "Flaking",
        "Peeling",
        "Softness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Peeling"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Very small flakes on plastered surfaces are called:",
    "options": [
        "Peeling",
        "Flaking",
        "Popping",
        "Uneven surface"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Flaking"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Efflorescence on plaster occurs due to soluble salts in plastering and building materials:",
    "options": [
        "Flaking",
        "Efflorescence",
        "Peeling",
        "Popping"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Efflorescence"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "A plaster defect observed mainly on interior plastered surfaces is:",
    "options": [
        "Softness",
        "Cracks",
        "Peeling",
        "Blistering"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blistering"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Wooden strips used for plastering purposes are made from well-seasoned wood:",
    "options": [
        "Metal laths",
        "Latex laths",
        "Rubber laths",
        "Wooden laths"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wooden laths"
},
{
    "number": 1,
    "question": "The process of filling hollow spaces in walls before plastering is called:",
    "options": [
        "Hacking",
        "Dubbing",
        "Blistering",
        "Peeling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dubbing"
},
{
    "number": 2,
    "question": "The height of a building’s roof is measured between:",
    "options": [
        "Roof and ground level",
        "Roof and floor level",
        "Above ground level to roof",
        "Roof to ground level"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Roof and floor level"
},
{
    "number": 3,
    "question": "The type of pointing in which a V-shaped projection is provided outside the wall surface is called:",
    "options": [
        "Recessed pointing",
        "Weather pointing",
        "V-pointing",
        "Tuck pointing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Weather pointing"
},
{
    "number": 4,
    "question": "Minimum slope of a prepared roof surface should be:",
    "options": [
        "1:200",
        "1:50",
        "1:1",
        "1:5"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:200"
},
{
    "number": 5,
    "question": "In brickwork, the spread of the foundation wall from the base to the outer edge does not exceed:",
    "options": [
        "1/2 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "2/3 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "1 horizontal to 1 vertical",
        "2 horizontal to 1 vertical"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1 horizontal to 1 vertical"
},
{
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Minimum strength of mortar used in load-bearing brickwork:",
    "options": [
        "50 N/cm²",
        "100 N/cm²",
        "150 N/cm²",
        "200 N/cm²"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "100 N/cm²"
},
{
    "number": 7,
    "question": "For exposed brick walls plastering, cement-sand mortar ratio should be:",
    "options": [
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:4",
        "1:6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:4"
},
{
    "number": 8,
    "question": "For brickwork using lime-sand mortar, the ratio is:",
    "options": [
        "1:1",
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:2"
},
{
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Nominal thickness of a brick wall in mm is:",
    "options": [
        "90 mm",
        "150 mm",
        "190 mm",
        "200 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "200 mm"
},
{
    "number": 10,
    "question": "In pebble dash (splash) finish, the commonly used size of pebbles is:",
    "options": [
        "2–5 mm",
        "10–20 mm",
        "20–35 mm",
        "30–50 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10–20 mm"
},
{
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Pebble dash finish is also known as:",
    "options": [
        "Dry dash finish",
        "Rough cast finish",
        "Wet dash finish",
        "Splash dash finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dry dash finish"
},
{
    "number": 12,
    "question": "Which type of plaster finish is used for plaster finishing?",
    "options": [
        "Smooth cast finish",
        "Pebble dash",
        "Scraped finish",
        "Textured finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Textured finish"
},
{
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Mortar ratio for the final coat in finishing is:",
    "options": [
        "1:3 / 2:3",
        "3/2 :1:3",
        "1:3 / 2:4",
        "1:1 / 2:3"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:3 / 2:3"
},
{
    "number": 14,
    "question": "Rough cast finish is also known as:",
    "options": [
        "Dry dash finish",
        "Pebble dash",
        "Spatter dash finish",
        "Textured finish"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Spatter dash finish"
},
{
    "number": 15,
    "question": "Thickness of second coat in sand-faced finish:",
    "options": [
        "4 mm",
        "8 mm",
        "12 mm",
        "15 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "8 mm"
},
{
    "number": 16,
    "question": "First coat in sand-faced finish is applied using cement-sand mortar ratio:",
    "options": [
        "1:2",
        "1:3",
        "1:1",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:4"
},
{
    "number": 17,
    "question": "In smooth cast finish, steel trowels are not recommended for external rendering:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "True"
},
{
    "number": 18,
    "question": "In sand-faced finish, second coat of plaster is applied after curing the first coat for:",
    "options": [
        "7 days",
        "15 days",
        "21 days",
        "27 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "7 days"
},
{
    "number": 19,
    "question": "Mortar ratio for smooth cast finish is:",
    "options": [
        "1:2",
        "2:3",
        "1:3",
        "1:4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1:3"
},
{
    "number": 20,
    "question": "In three-coat plastering, the first coat is called:",
    "options": [
        "Rendering coat",
        "Floating coat",
        "Setting coat",
        "Finishing coat"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rendering coat"
},
{
    "number": 21,
    "question": "In devil float finish, the projection from the surface is approximately:",
    "options": [
        "3 mm",
        "5 cm",
        "7 mm",
        "10 mm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "3 mm"
},
{
    "number": 22,
    "question": "The “knee” is also called:",
    "options": [
        "Gauging trowel",
        "Floating rule",
        "Floating float",
        "Laying trowel"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Floating float"
},
{
    "number": 23,
    "question": "Five types of metal floats are usually used for good workmanship:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 24,
    "question": "Blade size of a metal float is:",
    "options": [
        "10 cm × 20 cm",
        "20 cm × 40 cm",
        "10 cm × 30 cm",
        "30 cm × 50 cm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "10 cm × 30 cm"
},
{
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Trowel is made of wood:",
    "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "False"
},
{
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Metal float is also known as:",
    "options": [
        "Gauging trowel",
        "Laying trowel",
        "Reducing trowel",
        "Floating rule"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Laying trowel"
},
{
    "number": 27,
    "question": "Which tool is used for finishing small areas or less quantity of material?",
    "options": [
        "Gauging trowel",
        "Gauging float",
        "Metal float",
        "Skimming float"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gauging trowel"
},
{
    "number": 28,
    "question": "Parian cement plaster is obtained when POP is calcined with:",
    "options": [
        "Pearl ash",
        "Alum",
        "Borax",
        "Petroleum"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Borax"
},
{
    "number": 29,
    "question": "Martin cement plaster is obtained when POP is calcined with:",
    "options": [
        "Pearl ash",
        "Alum",
        "Borax",
        "Boren"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pearl ash"
},
{
    "number": 30,
    "question": "The hole formed in the surface of popping plaster is:",
    "options": [
        "Circular",
        "Conical",
        "Cylindrical",
        "Rectangular"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Conical"
}

























]